<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A seasonable warning and word of advice to all papists, but most especially to those of the kingdome of France; for them to turn from their idolatry, and gross superstition, and speedily to repent, and hast to meet the Lord by amendment of life, least he come on them, and smite them unawares ... / Charles Baily.</title>
            <author>Bayley, Charles, 17th century.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76237</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1473A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R170471</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45097541</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45097541</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171156</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76237)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171156)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2562:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A seasonable warning and word of advice to all papists, but most especially to those of the kingdome of France; for them to turn from their idolatry, and gross superstition, and speedily to repent, and hast to meet the Lord by amendment of life, least he come on them, and smite them unawares ... / Charles Baily.</title>
                  <author>Bayley, Charles, 17th century.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 66 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London; :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Anti-Catholicism --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171156:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Seaſonable Warning AND WORD OF Advice to all Papiſts, BUT Moſt eſpecially to thoſe of the Kingdome OF FRANCE; FOR Them to turn from their Idolatry, and groſs Superſtition, and ſpeedily to Repent, and haſt to meet the Lord by amendment of Life, leaſt he come on them, and ſmite them unawares.</p>
            <p>Which is good Counſel from a Friend to your ſouls, and a Lover of that which would make for your eternal welfare. CHARLES BAILY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed in the Year, 1663.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:171156:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171156:2"/>
            <head>A Seaſonable Word IN Love to all PAPISTS, who are ſcattered on the face of the Earth, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to thoſe of the Kingdom of FRANCE.</head>
            <p>OH ye Prieſts of the Nation, my controverſie is againſt you, ſaith the Lord God of Heaven and Earth, my fury is kindled againſt you, which you ſhall never be able to quench, ſaith the Allmigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; your Idolatry is a noiſomneſs unto me, and your prayers are an abomination in my ears; your Croſſes and your Crucifixes, ſhall not be able to hide you from my terrible irreſiſtable Judgements, which is nigh to be powred forth upon you, except you repent: <hi>Repent before the Decree</hi> be ſealed againſt you; ye make the people drunk with your abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Idolatry, ſaith the Lord God, therefore will <hi>I make you drunk with my fury,</hi> which ſhall be powred forth upon you, which you ſhall in no wiſe eſcape: weeping and howling ſhall be heard amongſt you, <hi>becauſe you have made the Innocent to weep, ſaith the Lord:</hi> Your ſtrong ſecurity ſhall become as rotten ſticks before me; And while ye ſhall cry peace peace, ſuddain deſtruction ſhall come upon you: the fire of my jealouſie is already kindled in your borders, which ſhall never be put out, untill it hath conſumed you root and branch, <hi>ſaith God Allmighty;</hi> whoſe power hath ſet
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:171156:3"/>bounds to the Sea, and ſaith to the proud waves thereof, <hi>Hitherto ſhall ye go, and no further;</hi> who will alſo bind and limit your pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ſo that it ſhall not paſſe the determined counſel of my God: Though you kick againſt him, and ſay in your hearts, Who is the Lord that we ſhould obey him? <hi>Know ye,</hi> he is the ſame as ever he was, in Might, in Power, in Glory, in Majeſty, in Dominion, and in Dread; who will make all Nations to tremble before him, and will render to every man according to his works; an hypocrite ſhall have a hypocrites portion, for he ſhall not be able to hide from his <hi>dreadfull preſence;</hi> nor a falſe god ſhall not be a cover for them, <hi>ſaith the Lord;</hi> who will roar out of his holy habitation; and for his own names ſake will he ariſe, yea like a man of war, and none ſhall be able to ſtand before him in Judgement; an Idolater ſhall have an Idolaters portion; money, nor favour, ſhall not be able to plead the cauſe of any, <hi>ſaith the Lord,</hi> but nakedly ſhall every one be judged and receive according to the deeds done in the body, whether they are good or evil; an <hi>Hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Prieſt,</hi> ſhall have an hirelings portion; an unbeliever, an unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers portion; and a deceiver, a deceivers portion; the lyar, a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars portion; they ſhall all be caſt into the Lake, <hi>ſaith the Lord God,</hi> where there ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth for ever. The mighty and terrible day of Gods vengeance is come, <hi>Therefore Awake,</hi> Awake ye people, awake and conſider what you are a doing; will an Idol ſave you? or an Image deliver you? <hi>ſaith the Lord;</hi> ſurely nay, the Image and the Image-maker ſhall periſh; the Idol and the Idolater ſhall have their reward together; <hi>In vain ſhall ye cry, when ye would be heard, ſeeing ye refuſe to hear when I call upon you, ſaith the Allmighty:</hi> Your prayers to <hi>Mary, John</hi> and <hi>James,</hi> and to the reſt of your imagined Saints, ſhall ſtand you in no ſtead at all; but on the contrary, ſhall adde <hi>to your condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> ſeeing you have choſen to your ſelves other Advocates and Mediators, then my Son whom I have given for a Covenant of Light to all Nations, that he might be your Salvation to the ends of the Earth. Hear, and give ear, ye dull and uncircumciſed in heart and ears: Is there any other name given under Heaven for Salvation <hi>but His?</hi> He is the Light of the world, and he enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth every one that cometh into the world, which Light ſhineth
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:171156:3"/>into every one of your Conſciences, checking and reproving every one of you for ſin and evill, though never ſo ſecret or private; can any forgive when by this Light you are condemned? Surely nay, ſeeing it is my true and <hi>Faithfull Witneſſe</hi> in every one of you, which judgeth righteouſly between me and you, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons, <hi>ſaith the Lord;</hi> drunkard it condemns thee for thy drunkenneſſe; lyar it condems thee for thy lying; ſwearer for thy ſwearing; glutton for thy gluttony; and whatſoever is ſin or evil it condemneth in you, whether pride, preſumption, hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, or covetouſneſſe which is idolatry; it condemns the evil, and juſtifies the good; therefore ſhall ye be left without excuſe in the day of <hi>Judgement;</hi> though ye may buy pardons of men, <hi>yet will not I pardon you, ſaith the Lord God, Except you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This, from the Lord</hi> is a Warning to you all; therefore while you have time prize it, leaſt the day of your viſitation paſſe over your heads unawares, and you be left to periſh for ever: <hi>Mark the Word ever,</hi> and lay it to heart before it be too late; therefore be you warned whileſt love and mercy is ſtretched out towards you, Prieſt and People, Kings, Potentates and Rulers, from the leaſt to the greateſt; for if you refuſe and reject this tender vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation of love, the dreadful ſword of Judgement ſhall bring you down, <hi>ſaith the Lord;</hi> for the Lord is riſen to rule and reign over all Nations, and none ſhall be able to ſtand before him; though the Prieſt preach for hire, and the Judges judge for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and both take counſel againſt the innocent, and ſo between Head and Tail, the whole Body is bound down under oppreſſion, yet a day of reſtoration is coming, and the yoak of oppreſſion and the burden thereof, ſhall be taken off from the necks of the poor and needy, that they may look towards me, <hi>ſaith the Lord,</hi> who will aſſuredly plead the cauſe of the afflicted, and deliver him from the hands of him which is too ſtrong for him. Theſe things will the Lord do for his own names ſake, that he might be known amongſt the ſons of men, for he hath been more a ſtranger a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, (though he hath created them) then the Ox is to the Owner, or the Aſſe to his Maſters Crib; many have profeſſed him in name, but in <hi>nature are wholly degenerated from him,</hi> there
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:171156:4"/>is more than cauſe enough in this unrighteous generation, for the righteous to be grieved, and his ſoul dayly vexed to behold the wicked converſation of the Inhabitants of the Earth, and none more than they who go under the name of Chriſtians, from the head to the foot of them; and all this chiefly happens from that curſed <hi>Harlot Rome,</hi> for all Nations profeſſing the name of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, hath been made drunk with the Cup of her fornication, which they have deeply drank off; the one part of which are called <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who are ſtark drunk with worſhiping of Images, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving of dayes and times, and men, and are ſo horribly bewitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as to give money for pardons for ſins, as may evidently be ſeen in <hi>Rome,</hi> and all the Popes Dominions, but chiefly in <hi>Italy,</hi> where they may have Indulgences for as little, or as much as they will, and ſome Indulgences perpetual, As I have ſeen written in Greek Characters over an Idols-Houſe door, belonging to <hi>Rome:</hi> And through ſuch witchcraft and wickedneſſe as this is, the people are ſtrengthned in their ſins, and glory therein. Oh! the Holy Spirit of the Lord is grieved with theſe things, who hath ſaid, <hi>I will ariſe, and eaſe me of my Adverſaries.</hi> And this is the fruits of that place which the people blaſphemouſly call <hi>The Holy City,</hi> which aboundeth as much in open whoredome, and more in Idolatry, than any City upon the face of the whole Earth; yea, whoredome is <hi>tollerated without any manner of Contradiction at all;</hi> and every Idoll-Maſſe-Houſe is a ſhelter for murder, and if any murderer get but into one of them, the <hi>Prieſts are by a Law</hi> bound to be a ſhelter unto them; this, and ſuch like is the fruits of that place, which people ſo much admire, ſo that many leave their own Native Countrey to ſee it, and when they are come thither, they are carried to admire a great Image of Braſſe, which they ſay is the Image of <hi>Saint Peter,</hi> and in honour to it fall down on their knees, and kiſſe its feet, which ſhews they are ignorant of the Image which <hi>Peter</hi> bare, (who was a Son of God) and of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Doctrine, who ſaid, <hi>Little Children keep your ſelves from Idols; what agreement hath the Temple of God with Idols? For ye are the Temple of the living God,</hi> as God hath ſaid, <hi>I will dwell in them, and walk in them, and I will be their God, and they ſhall be my People,</hi> John 5.21. 1 Cor. 2.16. &amp; Levit. 26.12. Wherefore I ſay
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:171156:4"/>unto you People, Come out from amongſt theſe things, for God will cut off the names of the Idols out of the Land, <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.2. and the makers of Idols ſhall go into confuſion; therefore ceaſe from theſe pilgrimages, which tend but to the worſhiping of Idols; and many under a pretence of this, go up and down the Countrey begging, untill ſome of them are ready to ſtarve, and others ſteal, where they can get an opportunity, and all under the name of the <hi>Holy Cauſe:</hi> And they who perform this pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, are the moſt ſtrict of them; after they have prayed to Images, and bowed to ſtocks and ſtones, bring away a few Beads and Images, and it may be kiſſe the Popes foot, whom they ſay is <hi>Peters Succeſſor,</hi> who was the Temple of God, and could not bow to an Idol, as he doth; therefore being meaſured by the line of true Judgement, he will be found to be the Temple and <hi>Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour of the Devil,</hi> elſe he would not bow to Idols, and teach others ſo to do, which ſheweth nothing elſe but the <hi>Succeſſion of the Man of Sin,</hi> even the Antichriſt, for all his actings are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely againſt Chriſt, and the holy Apoſtles, and Prophets of God, for they ſought not the honour and riches of this world, not the greatneſſe thereof, but in all things ſought to be humbled, that God alone might be exalted and honoured over all; for Chriſt ſaid, <hi>How can ye believe whileſt ye ſeek honour one of another?</hi> And ſaid this of himſelf, <hi>He received not honour from man,</hi> John 5.5, 41, 44. And they which did receive honour one of another, were ſo far from being Chriſts Diſciples, of <hi>Peters</hi> Succeſſors, that it plainly appears that they were not Believers, becauſe they ſought not the honour which cometh from God only; for when they ſought to make Chriſt an earthly King, <hi>who ſought his Fathers glory in all things,</hi> he therefore denyed the earthly honours which men would have put upon him, and hid himſelf from them. And <hi>Peter,</hi> when <hi>Cornelius</hi> fell down before him, <hi>Peter</hi> took him up, ſaying, <hi>Stand up, I my ſelf alſo am a man,</hi> Act. 10.26. So did the Angel forbid <hi>John,</hi> bidding him worſhip God, though he was one of them who kept the <hi>Commandements of God:</hi> Chriſt Jeſus, and all who followed him, forſook all earthly poſſeſſions, and were ſo far from being honoured of men, that they were hated, perſecuted, reviled, and ſhamefully entreated of men: But the Pope when
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:171156:5"/>he was Elected, though in worldly pomp before, yet entereth into greater, and is honoured and worſhiped by men, and cauſeth others to be perſecuted, impriſoned, and put to death; witneſſe one of the dear Servants of the Lord, called by name <hi>John Luff,</hi> who came to <hi>Rome</hi> as he was moved of the Lord, with his dear Brother <hi>John Parrot,</hi> who only deſiring to ſpeak with the Pope, were taken Priſoners; from whence the ſaid <hi>John Luff</hi> was taken and hanged ſecretly; and to cover this ſame wicked murder, they ſaid, <hi>He ſtarved himſelf to death;</hi> but this their ſecret murder they could not hide from the All-ſeeing eye, who revealed their ſecret murder unto me, and commanded me to faſt for a witneſſe againſt them; which I did in their own Priſon-Houſe, or Hoſpital of Mad-men, where they held me in Chains for no other cauſe, but for tendring my body for my Brother, as I was commanded of the Lord; they having detained him about three years Priſoner, in which time his ſufferings are hard to be uttered with the tongue of man; neither could it hardly enter into the hearts of men, if it were to be told unto them; for I believe from <hi>Adams</hi> day, of all the ſufferings of the holy men of God, the like could hardly be paralel'd, the whippings, buffetings and bruiſes, which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived amongſt them; yet I believe the dayly grief of his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſoul, was more than all his outward ſufferings; and all this plainly maketh them to appear, not to be Chriſt-like, but wholly againſt him, for his. Spirit is the Spirit of meekneſſe, love, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance, peace, long-ſuffering and forgiveneſſe; for he teacheth to forgive enemies, and to pray for them; yea, even for them that would ſhamefully entreat us; in this the Pope plainly appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not to be Chriſt-like, but contrary unto him, and ſo <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and againſt Chriſt,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>Bleſſe and curſe not;</hi> but the Pope curſeth thoſe which will not be ſubject unto him: and Chriſt ſaid, <hi>He came not to deſtroy mens lives, but to ſave them;</hi> and alſo ſaid, <hi>Swear not at all;</hi> but the Pope ingages men to ſwear, to fight and deſtroy men, ſo long as they live; witneſſe the Knights of <hi>Malta,</hi> who are alſo forbidden to marry, which <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, was a <hi>Doctrine of Devils;</hi> and in this alſo he plainly appeareth to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely againſt Chriſt, who had not whereon to lay his head in this world; but the Pope is not contented to have ſeveral houſes for
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:171156:5"/>himſelf to dwell in, but inricheth all his poſterity, purchaſing to one of his kindred a Prince-ſhip; and by this it appeareth, he hath not forſaken all, but covets all, or as much as in him lyeth to have: Chriſt when he rode was contented with an Aſſe, but the Pope when he goeth forth, though but a mile or two, is carried by men, and notwithſtanding hath ſeveral Horſes to attend upon him, and a Coach with ſix pompered Horſes to tend upon him empty, which is a horrid ſhame for any ſingle eye to behold in ſuch a one, who taketh upon him the name of <hi>Chriſts Vicar</hi> upon Earth: did he do it only in the name of an Earthly Prince, his abomination would not be altogether ſo great; but this ſheweth him to be in the way of the vain Heathen, and not a man of God, nor God-like in theſe actions; for <hi>Paul</hi> when he was called of God into his holy Miniſtry, he immediately obeyed the Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly voyce, and went and preached the Goſpel, and not go and ſhut himſelf up in great poſſeſſions, and there give forth Indulgences for pardons for ſins; but on the contrary declared the terrors of the Lord againſt all ſin, and ſaid, <hi>Such as men ſowed, ſuch ſhould they reap; if they ſowed to the fleſh, they ſhould of the fleſh reap cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, but if they ſowed to the Spirit, they ſhould reap life everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting;</hi> And alſo ſaid, That <hi>the wages of ſin is death:</hi> So that this was far from giving pardons for ſins, as the Pope doth. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>The Heathen exerciſe Lordſhip one over another, but with you it ſhall not be ſo;</hi> ſpeaking to thoſe who had truly forſaken all to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him: <hi>He that will be greateſt among you, let him be ſervant to all; for he that exalteth himſelf ſhall be abaſed, and he that abaſeth himſelf ſhall be exalted,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, who ſaid, <hi>Learn of me, for I am meek and lowly in heart.</hi> But with the Pope, and in his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there is Lording and exerciſing Lordſhip one over another, ſtriving who ſhall be greateſt amongſt them, as may be ſeen in the Eccleſiaſtical Courts in <hi>Rome,</hi> and elſewhere; where they are ſuing and ſtriving for honour; and by this they ſhew, they are wholly degenerated from the holy life of Chriſt, and his righteous Commands, who was a man of ſorrows and acquainted with grief, who <hi>ſought not his own glory, but the glory of him that ſent him, who was in travels, and tumults, in revilings and reproaches, giving his back to the ſmiter, and his cheeks to him which plucked off
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:171156:6"/>the hair; when he was reviled, reviled not again, when he was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted he entreated, and rendred not evil for evil, but ſought the good of all, and bore the contradiction of ſinners.</hi> This was his holy life and example, in the dayes of his fleſh, even in that body which was prepared him to do the will of his Father in, leaving all, his holy examples to follow. And now let the Pope and all his Adherents be meaſured by theſe fruits, they will be found wholly contrary, and againſt him; for inſtead of being acquainted with grief, they cauſe others to be grieved, and ſhut themſelves up in the fatteſt poſſeſſions, and they are fatned themſelves, as for the day of ſlaughter, ſporting themſelves with Wine and Muſick, deſtroying and devouring the fat of the Creation; this is apparent to every ſingle eye: And the Pope inſtead of bearing the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of ſinners, is one with them, and tollerates them in it, and ſuffereth none to come to ſpeak with him, without uſing a deal of flattering and deceit; and when they do obtain the liberty, muſt fall down and worſhip before him, and commonly kiſſe his toe, which is a horrible and deteſtable thing in the ſight of God; and inſtead of being perſecuted, cauſeth all to be perſecuted within his Dominion, that will not bow to theſe his wicked practices. And inſtead of ſubmitting his body to do the will of God, he pompers it dayly, <hi>Dives</hi>-like, whileſt the poor fatherleſs and wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow is oppreſſed; one need not go far to prove this, for it may be ſeen all over his Dominion, in the open ſtreets. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Freely ye have received, freely give;</hi> For his Miniſtry is a free Miniſtry; but the Popes is altogether contrary, for there is nought to be had of his Miniſters, but what the people muſt give money for; yea, when they have given money all the dayes of their life, they muſt give money to be prayed for after they are dead: Ages and Generations cannot paralel this horrible cheat, which they through deceit and hypocriſie deceive the hearts of the ſimple with; not an Age (I ſay) ſince the Apoſtacy can ſhew the like. And thus it is, the people are ſpending their money for that which is not bread, and their labour for that which profiteth not, ever learning, and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth, as plainly appeareth; for if they had come to the knowledge of the truth, the truth would have made them free, as <hi>ſaith Chriſt,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:171156:6"/>who preached no ſuch thing as Purgatory, neither did he tell peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they muſt give money for Maſſes to be ſaid for them after they were dead, to be had out from thence, as the Popes doctrine teacheth: So this is not with, but againſt Chriſt, and ſo Antichriſt, for ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Whoſoever is not with me, is againſt me;</hi> and the tree is known by its fruit; and this is a mark for evermore, for by their fruits we know them; though they may put on Sheeps cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yet inwardly they are ravening Wolvs, alienated from the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of truth, which would lead into all truth; and being from it erred, are given over to believe lies, that they might be damned, and ſo run greedily on in the way of deſtruction; and having loſt the key of true knowledge, have run on in the fleſhly know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and wiſdome, which is earthly, ſenſual, and deviliſh, and in it are at enmity againſt God; for that wiſdome never knew him, but on the contrary ever perſecuted them which did, <hi>it being the Seed of the Bond-woman,</hi> which perſecuted the Seed of the free-woman, from righteous <hi>Abel</hi> unto this day, enmity being put between the two Seeds for ever; and each Seed is manifeſtly known by its fruits; the one gendereth to ſin, bondage, and corruption; and the other keeps the Commandments of God; the one a Perſecutor and Murderer, and the other a Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferer: So here one may ſee the Pope and all his Adherents, as in a glaſs, what ſeed and lineage they are of, even by theſe their fruits, which to their faces teſtifies what Generation they are of; witneſs their Inquiſition, and places of tortures which they have; ſo that if any ſeem to ariſe or ſtir among them, and declare any thing which is not altogether ſuitable to their luſts, then preſently to the Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition with them, away with them, they are Hereticks, and deſerve not to live, and ſo impriſon, and ſhut them up, &amp; it is much if ever they come out, except by their cruel uſage they be made to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to their Wills; this is evident amongſt them, inſomuch that many of them have been kept many years, and not been told the cauſe why; for if they have but a Jealouſie of a man, he ſhall hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſcape their hands: And now what they have to be ſpoken againſt, let the moderate Reader ſeriouſly conſider, if there be any thing elſe but abominable Idolatry in all their Worſhip, even ſuch Idolatry, as all the Heathen of old never exceeded: As for Example, in <hi>Rome,</hi> which is the Fountain from whence all this abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:171156:7"/>ſprings, they pourtray the likeneſs of an Old Man upon a Wall, and they call him the <hi>Image of God the Father,</hi> with a Croſs before him, with the Portraicture of a dead man upon it, and the likeneſs of a Pigeon on the top of it, and this in their Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they call the <hi>Father, Son, and Spirit;</hi> And this being openly tollerated in <hi>Rome,</hi> the bordering Nations are made ſtark drunk with the ſame abominations and Idolatry: So that if one in love and in pity to their ſouls, ſpeak to reclaim them from their groſs darkneſs, they are ready to tear them in pieces, though it be plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manifeſt, that they are of thoſe who have changed the Glory of the Incorruptible God, into Images made like unto Corruptible men; wherefore God hath given them up to uncleanneſſe, through their loſt and corrupt hearts, who have changed the Truth of God into a lie, and do worſhip the Image which themſelves have made, more than the <hi>Creator, who is God bleſſed for ever.</hi> This is ſuch groſs darkneſs as was in <hi>Egypt,</hi> even ſuch as might be felt: And in God there is no ancientneſs of dayes, who is a Spirit, infinite, and eternal, <hi>who created all things by the Word of his power, and upholdeth all things thereby, unto this day. To whom will ye liken me?</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>Heaven is my Throne, and the Earth is my Footſtool; hath not my hand made all theſe things?</hi> all things being created in and by the Word of his Power, which is Chriſt Jeſus, for ſo is his Name, who was glorified by his Father before the World began, and <hi>is the expreſs Image of his Father,</hi> whoſe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs cannot be made by the hands of men; therefore it is horrible Idolatry for you to make the Image of a dead man, and ſay it is the Image of Chriſt, and ſo bewitch the minds of people with thoſe falſe conceptions and imaginations; woe be to them by whom theſe things are wrought and upheld, for the Vengeance and Indignation of the Lord God is kindled againſt them, for they are the unreaſonable Task-Maſters of <hi>Egypt,</hi> who keep the Seed in bondage and ſlavery, ſo that the people cannot come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the true God, that him only they might ſerve, honour and obey in all things, <hi>who is the only King, Judg, and Lawgiver of his people,</hi> who ſheweth mercy unto all who come unto him in his Sons Name; <hi>for there is no other Name given under Heaven for Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but his:</hi> And all who are in the praying to Saints, are in the wicked Idolatry, and do <hi>forſake the Fountain of living mercy, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:171156:7"/>have hewed to your ſelves Ciſterns, which will hold no Water:</hi> For the true Voyce ſaith, <hi>Come unto me all ye that are weary and heavy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and I will give you reſt:</hi> And ſaith the Prophet, <hi>All you which are a thirſt come, and you which have no money, come buy and eat, yea, come buy Wine and Milk without money and without price. Why do ye lay out your money for that which is not bread, and your labour for that which ſatisfieth not?</hi> Heare, and eat that which is good, and let your ſouls delight themſelves in fatneſs. <hi>Incline your ear, and come unto me, hear, and your ſouls ſhall live: And I will eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh with you my everlaſting Covenant, even the ſure mercies of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid: Behold, I have given him for a Witneſſe to the people.</hi> This is all free, even the free gift of God, <hi>Who hath ſo loved the World, that he hath given his only begotten Son into the World, that all through him might believe; for whoſoever believes in him, ſhall not abide in darkneſs, but ſhall have the Light of life; who is the Way, the Truth, and the Life; who hath enlightned every one who cometh into the World</hi> with his true Light; and they which turn to the Light wherewith Chriſt hath enlightned them, they come to Chriſt, who is the free Gift of God. This likes not the Pope and his Miniſters; for they make the people pay tenths of all their increaſe, beſides Money for Beads, Croſſes, and Crucifixes, and Money for pardon for ſins, and for Maſſes to be ſaid for them while they are alive, and after they are dead, and Money for Chriſtening of Children, as they call it, and Money for Marrying, and all that they doe; which thing ſheweth plainly, that his Miniſters are not like the Miniſters of the Goſpel, for that was and is a free Miniſtry, and the Miniſters thereof miniſtreth forth freely, as they have received, and are mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of God freely thereunto. So the Pope is not with Chriſt, but againſt him in all his actions; for Tithes were only due to <hi>Levi,</hi> and that from his Brethren; yet they were not <hi>Levi</hi>'s, but the Lords, and was to be put into the ſtore-houſes for to relieve the widow, the fatherleſs, and the ſtranger: but how the Pope and his Adherents doth this, let the wiſe in heart judge; who devour the Tenths and much more upon their luſts, as the Nations may witneſs againſt them; which plainly ſhews, they are neither of the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> nor of the Flock of Chriſt: And the Apoſtle, who was a Miniſter of the Goſpel, ſpeaking of <hi>Levi,</hi> ſaid, That Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood being changed, there is made of neceſſity a change of the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:171156:8"/>Law; for the Prieſthood being changed, it is evident that the Law is diſanulled which took them; ſo that this paying of Tithes, is but a uſurpation of thoſe which crope in (in this dark night of Apoſtacy) which Chriſt foretold us of, ſaying, <hi>The Night would come, wherein no man could work:</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> ſaw this coming in, <hi>For I know this,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that after my departure ſhall grievous Wolves enter in among you, not ſparing the Flock:</hi> And ſuch did come in, who taught things they ought not for filthy lucres ſake. The Pope and his Adherents will plainly appear to be of that ſtock, and ſpring from that curſed Root and Spirit, as his and their fruits will plainly manifeſt; for they who forſook the right way did run on in the way of <hi>Balaam,</hi> for gifts and rewards; but they have far exceeded all their Anceſtors, and will not be content with a gift and reward, but rob and take by force, where they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have it otherwiſe, ſo far as their power reacheth: And this running out of the way and commandement of God, is the cauſe why they profit not the people at all, though they creep into houſes and lead ſilly women captive, laden with ſin and divers luſts; and though they are ever learning, (of their Teachers) yet come not to the knowledge of the Truth, which would make them free from ſin and luſt, and bring into that life which was before a lie was. And this is not the fruit of the Popes Miniſters, for the furtheſt they bring people to, is to bring them to be zealous to pray to a dead ſtock or ſtone, which they make like unto men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and tell them it is the likeneſs or repreſentation of God and Chriſt, and the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> St. <hi>John,</hi> St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and the like; and the Miſtery of iniquity hath ſo wrought amongſt them, that though they manifeſtly proſtrate themſelves before them, yet they ſay it is not to them, which is darkneſs unheard of in Generations paſt: And they are not content to commit this abominable Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try themſelves, but would conſtrain all others to do the like; as witneſs the Proteſtants in this Nation, who are conſtrained to ſhun and avoyd the way, when one of theſe their Gods is carryed about, elſe the people are ready to ſtone them, if they do not put off their Hats, or bow unto them: Theſe things are cauſe of ſadneſs to the hearts of the righteous to conſider; therefore God will overturn it, and caſt it into the pit of confuſion, from whence it ſprang, even from <hi>Miſtery Babylon,</hi> where the Whore ſitteth, who hath made
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:171156:8"/>all Nations about her drunk with the Cup of her fornication, which hath been forced upon people, by the power of the Beaſt, through the Inchantments of the falſe Prophets; but their torment is near and haſtneth apace to come upon them, for the Whore and painted Harlot which rides upon the Beaſt, and the falſe Prophets which attend her, ſhall be taken and caſt into the lake, which burns with fire and brimſtone for ever: Theſe are true and faithfull ſayings, which ſhall ſhortly come to paſſe, and bleſſed ſhall all they be in that day which have not received the mark of the Beaſt in their <hi>hands,</hi> nor in their <hi>foreheads,</hi> for they onely ſhall live and reign for ever with him, whoſe right it is to reign over all Nations; and for his ſake will God overturn, overturn, overturn, untill his holy will be accompliſhed; and the Nations ſhall never ſee peace more untill that day, for the miſtery of iniquity hath fully wrought, and he that hath let ſhall be taken out of the way in this the day of Gods Allmighty power, in which he will threſh the Mountains to duſt, and will honour his Saints, ſo that they ſhall have power to bind Kings in Chains, and Nobles in Fetters of Iron, who alſo will turn the wiſdom of the wiſe backwards, and will make the Diviners mad, and turn the counſels of their <hi>Achitophels</hi> into fooliſhneſs. In this day the <hi>churl ſhall no more be called liberall,</hi> neither ſhall he that doth <hi>wickedly, be called good;</hi> light ſhall not be put for darkneſs, nor darkneſs for light, without a manifeſt Woe and Judgment upon him which doth it, <hi>ſaith the Lord God Allmigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> who hath been as a ſtranger amongſt the ſons of men, as though he had not created them, yea, more a ſtranger and unknown unto the chiefeſt of men, than the Ox is to his Owner, or the Aſſe to his <hi>Maſters Crib.</hi> It doth even pierce my heart to conſider the wofull degeneration of mankinde, who was created in the Image of his Creator, and whileſt he remained in that holy Image, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but righteouſneſs was wrought by him, and he enjoyed the peace of God in him, and in this ſtate there was no oppreſſion; <hi>but through diſobedience</hi> he was driven from his maker by giving ear to another Teacher, by which means he was lead unto luſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, and to commit it with greedineſs, yea to drink up iniquity as the Ox drinketh up water; ſo as he naturally did at firſt obey the will of his Creator, by which means he was wholly a Servant unto God, bringing forth the works of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and holineſſe; ſo through diſobedience, he became a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:171156:9"/>Servant to Satan bringing forth nothing but ſin and corruption, even to the grieving of his Creator; ſo that it repented him, that he had made man; yet he bore their iniquity untill the meaſure thereof was full, and then ſwept them away with the flood of his wrath; and from that day hath born and forborn the iniquity of many People and Nations, untill this your time, even untill the filling up of the largeſt meaſure of iniquity, that ever yet was known, ſo that righteouſneſs is not to be found in the earth, nor in the Inhabitants thereof; therefore as ſure as the righteous Judge of Heaven and Earth deſtroyed the old world with the flood of his wrath, ſo will he this by fire, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is already kindled in the Nations, though at preſent they perceive it not, but it ſhall overtake them unawares: Therefore this is ſent as a warning unto this Nation of <hi>France,</hi> that they may take warning thereby, and repent, leaſt they be conſumed by the flame and fire of Gods wrath and indignation, which is ready to break forth upon them.</p>
            <p>And now ye people of this Nation, ſeriouſly conſider (high and low, rich and poor, bond and free, male and female) what ye are a doing, and with the light of Chriſt Jeſus wherewith he hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned you, ſearch whoſe works ye are a doing, and who it is you obey, and whoſe command you have for the things you do, whether from God or from men; for aſſuredly according to the Traditions of men, God cannot be worſhipped nor ſerved, for God is a Spirit; <hi>And the true Worſhippers worſhip him in Spirit and Truth,</hi> and by ſuch only is he worſhipped; therefore ceaſe from all your Task-maſters which lay heavy burdens upon you, telling you that you muſt pray to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and to the Saints, ſaying ten Prayers to her, and one to God, ſhewing that they exalt her in their Imaginations above God; beſides this is clear againſt the Doctrine of Chriſt, who bid them ask in his name, for ſaith he, <hi>Whatſoever ye ask my Father in my Name, it ſhall be given you.</hi> (Mark that) and take good notice of it, <hi>for he is the only Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor between God and man,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.5. <hi>For there is one Mediator between God and man, the man Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> for he is the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of a better Covenant than that which ſtood in outward meats and obſervations, which is eſtabliſhed upon better promiſes; and for this cauſe he is the Mediator of the New Teſtament, that by means of death for the redemption of the tranſgreſſions that were
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:171156:9"/>under the firſt Teſtament, that they which are called might enjoy the promiſe of eternal Inheritance: Therefore people are to come to Jeſus the Mediator of the new Covenant, <hi>and to the blood of ſprinkling, that ſpeaketh better things than that of Abel;</hi> therefore ſee that ye refuſe not him that ſpeaketh from Heaven, who ſaith, <hi>What ye ask my Father in my Name, it ſhall be given you;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ceaſe from asking in any other name: Search and read, and be no longer deceived, for God is come to look for fruit in the earth, and every tree which is not found bearing fruit to God, ſhall be cut down, and caſt into the fire. Read the Parable of the Fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, and lay it to heart before it be too late, and ceaſe from your Taskmaſters which tell you a houſe of ſtone is a Church, contrary to the Scripture which ſayes the Church <hi>is in God, the ground and pillar of truth;</hi> you may ſee in this they alſo deceive you, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.1. For in the true Church, <hi>nothing that defileth can enter;</hi> but in yours, drunkards, lyars, and all manner of unclean perſons may enter. Thus you are deceived by the lying and lightneſſe of your Teachers, who through covetous practices make Merchandize of your ſouls; for were you truly inſtituted, you would come to know, that the Saints bodies are the Temple of the Holy Ghoſt, and their bodies was not for fornication (which is openly tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted amongſt you,) <hi>but for the Lord,</hi> and the Lord for the body; therefore you are ignorant of this Doctrine of <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>Know ye not that your bodies are the Members of Chriſt;</hi> for if you were not ignorant thereof, you would be afraid to make them the members of an Harlot, <hi>For who is joyned to an Harlot is one body, for two</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhall be one fleſh.</hi> Therefore repent and return to God, and then you will come to witneſs your bodyes the Temples of the Holy Ghoſt, which God will put in you, and you ſhall no more be your own, for through repentance you will come to know that ye are bought with a price, and ſo will come to glorifie God in your bodies and ſpirits, which then will be Gods, as you come to the blood of cleanſing, as the Saints of old did, and ſo did wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe God to live and walk in them, which was a true Chriſtians ſtate, for they were led by the Spirit of God, and ſo became the Sons of God; but if any come amongſt you now, and ſay they have the Spirit of God in them, ye make a mock at them, and ſay they are mad, and ſo are ready to ſtone them, though the true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:171156:10"/>did witneſſe the ſame, elſe they could not have been Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>For it is the life of Chriſt in the Creature which makes him a Chriſtian,</hi> through which he comes to witneſſe the promiſe of God to be fulfilled, which the Prophet <hi>Joel</hi> propheſied of, ſaying, <hi>Thus ſhall it come to paſſe, afterwards, that I will pour out my Spirit upon all fleſh, and your ſons and your daughters ſhall propheſie, your old men ſhall dream dreams, your young men ſhall ſee viſions; And alſo upon your ſervants and handmaids in thoſe dayes, will I poure out my Spirit.</hi> Therefore <hi>I in the Spirit</hi> do declare unto you my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey men, this acceptable day, that you may turn from your ſins and find mercy, that the powring out of the Spirit ye may come to witneſſe amongſt you, which will lead you into all truth, and from your deceitfull Teachers, ſo will you come to know the ſpirit of propheſie, as the Saints of old did, who were truly ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied through the blood of the Lamb; for ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> unto them, <hi>You may all propheſie one by one;</hi> which was the true Churches order.</p>
            <p>And againe, Your Prieſts tels you, you muſt look for teaching from them, but the Covenant of God is, That all his people ſhall be taught of him; <hi>For this ſhall be the Covenant that I will make with the Houſe of Iſrael: After theſe dayes</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>I will put my Law in their inward parts, and write it in their hearts, and I will be their God, and they ſhall be my People, and they ſhall no more teach every man his neighbour, and every man his brother, ſaying, know the Lord, for they ſhall all know me from the leaſt to the greateſt of them,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>For I will forgive their iniquities, and I will remember their ſins no more.</hi> And all the children of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant come to witneſſe this which is their great peace, for they that come to witneſſe the Anointing, need not mans teaching; but if this you ſhould come to witneſſe, your Prieſts ſhould ſoon be diſcovered, which is the cauſe they every way hold you in bondage and blindneſſe, <hi>being Miniſters thereof themſelves,</hi> as manifeſtly appeareth by their fruits, for were they Miniſters of light, they would bring people to the light, and ſo to the true knowledge of God, <hi>for God is light,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle; <hi>God is light,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and in him is no darkneſſe at all; and if we walk in the light, as he is in the light, then have we fellowſhip one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Mark, the Saints fellowſhip was in the light; therefore
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:171156:10"/>he that ſaith <hi>He knoweth God, and walketh in darkneſſe, is a lyar;</hi> for he that cometh to the light, cometh to know the teachings of God, which the everlaſting Miniſtry brings into. So here Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple you may meaſure your Prieſts by the Scriptures of truth.</p>
            <p>And again, Your Prieſts tell you, you muſt give money to pray for thoſe which are dead, which is an invention of the Devill, the deceiver, from whence that deceit ſprung, to make you believe there is a place called Purgatory, to be purged in, after you are dead, which thing is only taught for filthy lucres ſake; for the Scriptures no where ſpeak of a Purgatory for men to be purged in after they are dead, but on the contrary it ſaith, <hi>As the Tree falls, ſo it lyes, for ſuch as a man ſoweth, ſuch ſhall he reap;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the true Miniſtry was for to bring people to the Spirit of God, that ſo their ſowing might be to the Spirit, the fruits of which is life everlaſting. So here they were brought off from the works of the fleſh, by the vertue of the blood of Chriſt Jeſus, and came to be <hi>cleanſed from all ſin,</hi> for ſaith <hi>Paul, When you were ſervants of ſin, you were free from righteouſneſs,</hi> Rom. 6.20. (Mark) <hi>They were made free from ſin;</hi> ſo here was no need of a Purgatory to be purged from ſin after death, being made free from ſin while in the body, as <hi>Adam</hi> was, and as true Chriſtians were, who follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Chriſt through the regeneration, even to the witneſſing of the new-birth, <hi>which ſinueth not,</hi> as ſaith the Scriptures, <hi>He that is born of God ſinneth not, neither can he, becauſe his ſeed remaineth in him:</hi> And as we know that God is righteous, ſo we know that he that doth righteouſneſſe is born of him; and ſo this is the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans boldneſs in the day of Judgement, that as he is, ſo are they in this preſent world; ſo according to Chriſts words, they come to be perfect, <hi>even as their Father which is in Heaven is perfect.</hi> And this is a true Chriſtians life, to be like Chriſt, to live in him as he doth in the Father; ſuch only are Chriſtians, <hi>who witneſſe Chriſt in them,</hi> as the Father is in him; for, people read and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, as you prize the ſalvation of your precious ſouls, <hi>For the ſoul that ſinneth, ſhall dye,</hi> as ſaith the Prophet. Likewiſe your Prieſts tell you, you muſt honour and invoke the Saints that are dead, and get pieces of their bones to carry about you, &amp; ſuch vanity as this do they feed you with, for ſaith Chriſt, <hi>The fleſh profiteth nothing, but the Spirit quickneth.</hi> This he ſpake to them who were looking at
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:171156:11"/>his fleſh outwardly; but did you once come to the Spirit, which only profiteth, you would come to know the will of God fulfilled in you, which is your ſanctification, and then you will be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to make reliques of one anothers cloaths, fleſh or bones, but will come to know the true Sanctification to be in and by the Word, which is Chriſt; for ſo Chriſt prayed, <hi>Sanctifie them by thy word, thy word is truth;</hi> and they who come to know the truth, come to <hi>know the word in them,</hi> which ſanctifies them through ſoul and body; and this word <hi>David</hi> knew right well, and the vertue thereof, who ſaid, <hi>Thy word have I hid in my mouth, that I might not ſin againſt thee.</hi> And if you once come to the knowledge and power of his word, it will keep you alſo from ſinning againſt God, which is the true ſanctified ſtate; and this is no new Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, for <hi>Moſes</hi> the true Servant of the Lord preached the ſame to the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſaying, <hi>The word is nigh you, even in your mouths and in your hearts:</hi> (Mark) the <hi>word</hi> was nigh them, even in them; and this was the word of faith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; he that comes to the word of faith, comes to that which puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies and makes clean; and here the ſanctification comes to be witneſſed in the particular, by which means the perfect unity comes to be known and enjoyed with the Saints, <hi>with Chriſt in God;</hi> ſo here will be no need to invoke one another, but all will be asked in the name of Chriſt <hi>the power of God,</hi> which power will infallibly be heard and anſwered of God, <hi>For whatſoever ye ſhall ask of the Father in my name, it ſhall be given you,</hi> ſaith Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, who is the true Teacher and Shepherd of the ſoul, even of all that come unto him, who will teach them how to pray, and to whom, even God the Judge of all: And by this you may ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently prove your Pope and Prieſts Doctrine, to be none of Chriſts, but contrary to him, which is <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> You are alſo forbidden by them meats and marriage, which the <hi>Apoſtle ſaid</hi> was <hi>a Doctrine of Devils,</hi> ſpeaking lyes in hypocriſie unto you, having their <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences</hi> ſeared with an hot Iron, for they forbid you that which God hath created to be received <hi>with thanksgiving of them which believe and know the truth; for every Creature of God is good, if it be received with thanksgiving,</hi> for it is ſanctified <hi>by the Word of God and Prayer,</hi> 1 Tim. 3.4, 5. <hi>For unto the pure, all things are pure;</hi> For they that come to the purifying, come to know all
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:171156:11"/>things pure unto them; but to the impure, nothing is pure, their minds and conſciences being defiled; (therefore men knowing this) but who comes to the true hope which purifies even as Chriſt is pure, which is a purifying throughout in ſoul and body in this life, yea, and gives Dominion over Sin, Hell, Death and the Devil; and he that witneſſeth this hope in him, needs not a Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory to purge him after he is dead, for he comes to be <hi>purified as Chriſt is pure,</hi> as alſo ſaith the Scripture. This is the true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an hope, whereby he comes to be-purified and made clean, as alſo knowing that God hath created all things for them that fear him; but to the impure (as I have ſaid) nothing is pure unto them; though they may lye and ſay they faſt when they only forbear one ſort of meat, and eat another, which will but adde to their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation; and their Prieſts which doth teach them to lye, will not be able to deliver them, but the Teachers and the Teached ſhall periſh together, <hi>except they repent,</hi> for the Lake is prepared for the lyar; for is it not damnable lying and hypocriſie for men to ſay they faſt, when they only forbear one ſort of meat, and eat ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? Is not fiſh fleſh? <hi>Doth not the Apoſtle call it ſo?</hi> And in this your pretended faſt, you drink Wine, and feaſt your ſelves without fear, whileſt ſome have hardly bread to eat. Theſe things are an abomination unto the Lord God of Heaven and Earth, for his wrath you ſhall ſurely feel for this hypocriſie, <hi>except you repent;</hi> though you ſay you hope to be ſaved, that ſhall ſtand you in no ſtead in the dreadful day of vengeance which is very nigh you, <hi>For the hypocrites hope ſhall periſh,</hi> as ſaith the Scripture; and though ſome of you who are more zealouſly given than others, may faſt and hang down your heads like a Bulruſh for a day, <hi>Phariſee</hi>-like, and give almes to be ſeen of men, which is as though you offered up Swines blood, or as the cutting off of a Dogs neck, it being in that nature which crucifies the Juſt in your ſelves, even that which would lead you (out of obſervation of dayes and times) up to God, which was before time was; and untill you come to take diligent heed to this juſt principle of God in your ſelves, which condemns for all hypocriſie, ſin and deceit, (profeſs what you will, <hi>it will ſtand you in no ſtead,</hi> ye though you ſhould give all your goods to the poor, and your bodies to be burnt, it will avail you nothing) for it leads all who diligently follow it, to do to all
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:171156:12"/>men, as they would others ſhould do unto them, which is the true Chriſtian life, in which only all works are accepted with God, for it is the fulfilling the Law and the Prophets; for the Law was added becauſe of tranſgreſſion, and untill there be a fulfilling of it in you, ye are under the curſe, profeſs what you will: Some may ſay this is an hard ſaying, who can bear it? Did not Chriſt Redeem us from under the curſe of the Law? and was not he made manifeſt for that end? I anſwer, to this end was the Son of God made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in the fleſh, to condemn ſin in the fleſh, that the righteouſneſs of the Law might be fulfilled in us, and all who come to know the teachings of God in the Spirit, know him to fulfill the Law, not to aboliſh or deſtroy it, in as much as it is righteous, and layeth hold on nothing but the tranſgreſſor to condemnation; therefore ſaith <hi>Paul, The Miniſtration of condemnation was glorious in its time;</hi> and this all the Saints and holy men of God did witneſs, Chriſt the righteouſneſs of God manifeſt in them, who did all their works in them, and for them, and by which all boaſting was excluded, becauſe <hi>It is not of him that willeth, nor him that run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, but in God that ſheweth mercy;</hi> the ſtrength of the Creature being to ſtand ſtill, bearing his dayly croſs, and thereby is made ſubject unto him <hi>who is able to ſave to the utmoſt all who come unto him in and through Chriſt,</hi> the Door, Power, and Wiſdome of God, who is the Light of the World: Therefore Salvation is not of works, but of grace, which is freely tendered to all mankind upon the face of the whole earth; <hi>for the grace of God that bringeth Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation hath appeared to all men, teaching us, that denying ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, we ſhould live ſoberly, righteouſly and godly in this preſent world; looking for that bleſſed hope, and the glorious appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the great God, and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, who gave himſelf for us, that he might redeem us from all iniquity, and purifie unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a peculiar people, zealous of good works,</hi> Tit. 2.11, 14. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were your Prieſts truly in the knowledge of God and his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, they would bring you to the knowledge of the Miſtery that hath been hid from Ages, which without controverſie is great, to wit, <hi>God Manifeſt in the fleſh,</hi> which was Chriſt in the Saints, the Hope of glory; and were you rightly inſtructed, you would come to know the riches of the glory of this Miſtery, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.27. for it would be your glory alſo, for it was the Saints hope of their
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:171156:12"/>glory, which hope will perfectly ſave you, and cleanſe you from ſin and evill, and thereby purifie you <hi>as Chriſt is pure;</hi> for this is the only and true hope, which anchors and ſtays the ſoul: And if you once come to this, then their Trade is ſpoyled; but they are as ignorant of it as you your ſelves: but the true Miniſters of the New Covenant preached nothing but what themſelves were wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of; therefore ſaith <hi>John, That which was from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, which we have heard, which we have ſeen with our eyes, and looked upon, and our hands have handled of the Word of life,</hi> that they did declare to the people, that the people might come to have fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with them, and their fellowſhip was with the Father and with his Son, becauſe their living and walking was in the Light, as God was in the Light, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> And this is the end of the true Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters miniſtry, who were Miniſters of the Spirit, <hi>and not of the Letter,</hi> neither did they boaſt of other mens ſayings made ready to their hands, as your Prieſts do, for what they pray, preach, and ſpeak unto you, are other mens works, yea, the greateſt part of your worſhip, which is the Maſſe, and the reſt; thus they make merchandiſe of your for diſhoneſt gain, made, and put in by the will of men, and by the will of men are upholden, and guarded by a Law that none muſt ſpeak againſt their open abominations: but the day of the Lord hath overtaken them as a thief in the night, and their works of darkneſs muſt, and will be brought to light, let them fence themſelves never ſo wiſely, and dig as deep as Hell for Counſel; yea, the day is come, and though they ſhould exceed all their fore-fathers in burning and perſecution, it would but add to their torment, for the Sword of the Lord is drawn, and will never be ſheathed until it hath cut them up root and branch, yea, the cup of Gods fury is filled even to the brim, and they muſt drink the dregs thereof; though they be made and upholden by men, yet of a truth men ſhall not be able to ſave them; for let them daub and flatter never ſo much, to make them a wall or ſhelter, the wall which is daubed and the daubers ſhall fall together: This of a truth, is the determination, will, and counſel of the moſt high God; though bryers and thorns do ſet themſelves againſt him in battel, all ſhall be in vain, for the breath of his mouth ſhall burn and conſume them for ever; for he of a truth is ariſen, <hi>before whom all Nations are as the drop of a bucket, and as the ſmall duſt of the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:171156:13"/>Behold he taketh the Iſles as a very little thing, yea all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons before him are as nothing, and they are counted to him leſſe than nothing, and vanity: He meaſureth the waters in the hollow of his hand, and meeteth out the Heavens with a ſpan, and comprehendeth the duſt of the earth in a meaſure, and weigheth the mountains in ſcales, and the hills in a ballance.</hi> I ſay, even he whoſe preſence fills Heaven and Earth, is riſen to plead the cauſe of the Innocent, the poor and the needy, and to make way for the meek, that they only may reign over the works of his hands, in his Son, who muſt, and ſhall reign over all for ever; and this will he perfect for his own names ſake, the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it; therefore it is a vain thing for men to cloath themſelves ſome in one habit, and ſome in another; and one ſaith he is of ſuch an Order, and another ſayes he is of ſuch an Order, whileſt they are all in the order of ſin and uncleanneſſe, the root thereof ſtands firm and untouched within them, though they diſguiſe themſelves like ſo many Anticks in ſeverall ſhapes, more like men of unmodeſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment, than like men fearing God, which doth in no wiſe conſiſt in ſuch like diſguiſed habits, <hi>but in a clean heart;</hi> for <hi>The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wiſdom,</hi> which leads to the true underſtanding of the uſe of all the creatures of God, and how to uſe them in decency and true order, and in the moderation, for which end they were created and made, even to ſerve man, and man his Creator, in fear, with a clean heart and pure mind; but man being degenerated from this holy life, gets into habits and meats by diverſities, and calls ſome holyer than other, though in the beginning they were all created good, as it is written, <hi>Every creature of God is good, and nothing to be refuſed.</hi> But theſe men get into ſeveral habits, and call them holy, as though the wool that came from the ſheeps back availed any thing: and thus the Phariſees were in dayes paſt, in outward obſervations of dayes and things, and went in long robes, eſteeming one thing holyer than another, for which Chriſt rebuked them, ſaying, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it greater, the gift or the Altar which ſanctifieth the Gift?</hi> And likewiſe in thoſe days being ignorant of that which ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and maketh clean, by which all things comes to be ſanctified to the Creature, whether meat, drink or apparrel, through the uſe of which only they ſhould have had regard <hi>to the Giver,</hi> who regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:171156:13"/>not, nor reſpecteth the perſon of any man, much leſſe the cloathing, or meats, or drinks, which deſileth not the man; but of all Nations <hi>He that feareth God, and worketh righteouſneſſe, is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of him,</hi> as ſaith the Scripture: But theſe things the Apoſtles ſaw was crept in amongſt many in their dayes, as <hi>Touch not, taſt not, handle not,</hi> which thing had a fair ſhew, but it was but will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip, and voluntary humility, and nothing to the edifying of the body, and ſo by degrees hath crope in more and more, as the dark night of apoſtacy came in, which time Chriſt Jeſus ſaid <hi>would come, wherein no man could work.</hi> And alſo the Apoſtle ſaw before his deceaſe (as I ſaid before) even ſuch a falling away in his time, that he ſaid, <hi>All Aſia was turned from him.</hi> Likewiſe <hi>Peter, John,</hi> and <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeak of it; for <hi>John</hi> in his Revelation, <hi>ſaw all the world wandering after the Beaſt, and none could buy or ſell, but thoſe who received the mark of the Beaſt;</hi> yea ſuch will be the miſery of the ſons of men, who are wandering after him, ſaying, <hi>Who is able to make war with him?</hi> And the Harlot rides upon the Beaſt <hi>cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with Scarlet,</hi> with the Cup full of abomination and filthineſs in her hand, which hath made all <hi>Nations drunk.</hi> Let him which hath wiſdome, read and underſtand, and conſider whether the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Cardinals</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> doth not wear her Livery without and within, <hi>yea or nay;</hi> are they not built upon blood, and to this very day are thirſting after it? if not, what means their Inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſecret places of murder? yet they themſelves will ſhew and tell of the place they call by the name of <hi>Amphiatar,</hi> where they ſay the Chriſtians were put in in former times to be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with wild Beaſts, though the ſame they themſelves do at this very day, even to thoſe who have the leaſt deſire after the Lord, by which they come to miſturſt the Idolatrous way they are in; and if this be perceived amongſt them, then preſently he or ſhe is termed under the name of an Heritick, and then to the Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with them, where the wild bruit Beaſts ſet about them to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour them, though at firſt they may flatter and fawn upon them like a Dog, and if they ſee they cannot prevail with them that way, it is much if ever they eſcape their devouring hands; and this is not unknown to many: but the Lord God of Heaven and Earth is riſen to make inquiſition for the blood of the ſlain, and it is not the Inquiſition which ſhall be able to conceal it from him, for he
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:171156:14"/>will rip it open, and lay it deſolate for ever, ſo that it ſhall become a hiſs and a by-word by all the paſſers by, for it ſhall be made like their <hi>Amphiatar</hi> for ever, open and free, and Gods eternall Glory and Truth ſhall freely be declared in it, with free conſent every way; and this will the Lord work for his own Gloryes ſake, and none can prevent the Lords purpoſe, which he hath determined, for all the world hath wandered after the Beaſt, and hath given their glory and honour unto him; I ſay notwithſtanding all this, the Lord will raiſe up to himſelf an holy ſeed, which ſhall make war with him, and overcome him; his choſen ones have already read the number of his name, which is the number of a man, and all that riſe up and joyn in war with the Beaſt againſt them, woe, woe will be to them for ever. The Angels of the Lord are going forth with Commiſſion from the God of Heaven, to curſe the Earth becauſe of the abominations of the Inhabitants thereof. Therefore O ye people, be awakened and warned, and ſeriouſly conſider what you are a doing, for of a truth woe and vengeance will be powred out upon you in an unreſiſtable manner, <hi>except ye repent ſpeedily;</hi> therefore as one who is a follower of the Lamb through tribulations, do I warn you (in obedience to my King and Law-giver) <hi>to kiſſe the Son leaſt he be angry,</hi> that ye may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain mercy in this day of love and viſitation to the ſons of men; for the Lord hath certainly determined to reap the earth of all corruption, which aboundeth and ſuperaboundeth therein; the harveſt is fully ripe, and long hath the Lord born and forborn, and his righteous Spirit hath long been oppreſſed, even as a Cart is preſſed, which is laden with ſheaves; therefore will he plead with all fleſh with the ſword and with fire, <hi>which none ſhall be able to withſtand;</hi> therefore be ye warned that your ſouls may live.</p>
            <p>And though many of them make vows in their own wills, to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from meats and women, this ſhall ſtand them in no ſtead, for in words they ſay they will do this and that, but being <hi>out of Gods will,</hi> luſt burns in their hearts, they not being come to that which would ſubdue the evill in themſelves,; and theſe are they which the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, <hi>They promiſe others liberty, whileſt they themſelves are the ſervants of corruption; for of what a man is overcome, by the ſame he is brought in bondage,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.19.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:171156:14"/>for at beſt, they ſay they are of ſuch a Saints Order, which will avail them nothing, they not being ſanctified themſelves, were it ſo that Saints were of ſeveral Orders and Lifes, <hi>but that's an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute lye,</hi> and a falſe conception; and this is only to blind the minds of the ſimple-hearted, thereby to get the more ſeveral Inheritan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>and fat poſſeſſions to themſelves,</hi> by going in ſeveral habits, and going under ſeveral denominations, by which policy and deceit, (where they have been moſt believed &amp; received) they have got the fatteſt and beſt poſſeſſions, and notwithſtanding go a begging, and a roving up and down, and take and receive from them who have great families to maintain, which thing is grievous to be born in the Land; but God will judge for this hypocriſie and deceit, and eaſe the Land of this oppreſſion, <hi>of a Truth,</hi> and their lyes and feignedneſs ſhall be laid open to <hi>every eye;</hi> for the Saints were not of many Orders, but of one only true Order, which was truth in the <hi>Inward parts,</hi> which is the root and ground of Religion, in which they did not ſhut up themſelves in houſes, and live in idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and eat the bread thereof, which the poor laboureth hard for, and purchaſeth by the ſweat of their brows, and with it theſe men under a pretence of holineſs feed themſelves without fear; and this is not the order of Saints, but of <hi>belly-gods,</hi> for the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle writing unto the Saints, ſaith, <hi>He that will not work, let him not eat,</hi> He being an Example unto them; though he laboured in the Goſpel above many, yea, and the care of all the Churches were upon him, yet notwithſtanding his own hands miniſtred to his neceſſities, which is a witneſſe againſt the idle drones of this Generation, which you take for your Confeſſors, and they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to have power to abſolve you from your ſins, <hi>and are not clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from their own.</hi> Therefore hear and conſider all people, who are thus kept in blindneſſe and ignorance, there is nothing but the pure Holy Spirit of God, which is able, or can forgive ſins, for to it only is the power committed, and not unto you <hi>who live in ſins:</hi> And therefore be awakened out of this horrid deluſion; for Chriſt Jeſus ſaid to his Apoſtles, <hi>Whoſe ſins ye remit, they are remitted;</hi> they received alſo a Commiſſion from God to preach the Goſpel, which none can do without the gift of the Holy Ghoſt, which is only able to forgive, ſave and deſtroy; for though it was ſaid to <hi>Peter, Thou art Peter, and upon this Rock will I build my Church,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:171156:15"/>this was not ſpoken unto him as he was a fleſhly man, but as he had the revelation of the Holy pure Spirit of God, upon which the Church is built, <hi>for the Church is in God,</hi> who is the <hi>only ground and pillar of truth,</hi> againſt which the Gates of Hell can never pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, though they prevailed againſt <hi>Peter</hi> after them words were ſpoken unto him, ſo far as that he denyed his Maſter; ſo here, you that are not ſtark drunk and poyſoned with this conception, that the Incorruptible Church of God (which is only built with living ſtones, elect and precious, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> being the chief corner ſtone) is built upon a man, which is corrupt, for it is evident <hi>Peter</hi> is dead, and ſome of you ſay you have his bones amongſt you, which ſhews their foundation to be decayed, had it been upon his perſon, which never could be, but upon his ſpirit, by which he made that good confeſſion, <hi>That Chriſt was the Son of God,</hi> which none can truly do without, nor call him <hi>Lord.</hi> Therefore <hi>Pope, Cardinals, Monks, Jeſuites</hi> and <hi>Fryers</hi> of all ſorts come forth and vindicate your ſelves, and ſhew your Commiſſion for what you do, and from whom you had it, for from <hi>Peter,</hi> nor from Chriſt, you are never able to ſhew you had it, neither are you able to vindicate your Doctrine and Practice, <hi>no further then your Inquiſition Law, and Priſon will reach;</hi> all which weapons will fail you in the terrible day of vengeance, which is coming upon your heads; for as you have made the Inhabitants of the earth drink deep of the Cup of <hi>Miſtery Babylons Harlots,</hi> you likewiſe ſhall be made to drink deep of the Cup of Gods vengeance, even the dregs thereof ſhall be wrung out to you, and your nakedneſſe ſhall be laid open for every eye to behold it. And this is the word of the Lord God to you all, which can never be recalled, nor paſſe away unfulfilled upon your heads: Therefore Oh ye Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the Earth, haſt, haſt and repent, leaſt ye partake of her plagues; for if ye endeavour, and ſtrive to uphold her, ye ſhall of a truth partake of her Judgements.</p>
            <p>Again, I ſay be ye warned before it be too late, and turn to the Lord by true repentance, by forſaking and faſting from ſin, which if you do, there is rich mercy in ſtore for you, <hi>and plenteous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption in Chriſt Jeſus, who is the Light of the world, who hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned every one that cometh into the world</hi> with his true Light, which reproves for ſin and evill in the inward parts; and if you
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:171156:15"/>believe in it, and follow it, and give up wholly to be guided by it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you will become children of the Light, <hi>and have an Inheritance with the Saints in the Light;</hi> for the ſame which condemns you for ſin, would alſo purifie and cleanſe you from all ſin, for it is the blood of the Covenant which is plentifully ſhed for loſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done man; and untill this be witneſſed, even a purifying, waſhing and cleanſing from ſin, there is no forgiveneſs; for becauſe of tranſgreſſion, the Law was added; this is the truth of God unto you all ſent, amongſt you to no other end but that you might be ſaved, and come to the knowledge of the truth, which would make you free, and lead you out of the deceit of the deceiver, as to be no longer deceived by him. For ſeriouſly conſider, what have you from them whom you ſpend your time and ſubſtance about, but the ſight of a company of Images, which they make you make Idols of, by proſtrating your ſelves before them, which is abſolutely againſt the righteous Law of God, the Creator of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth? ſee the Scripture, <hi>Exodus</hi> 20. And thus you are fed as long as you feed them, and put in their mouths; but if you ever come to ceaſe from feeding their inordinate deſires, they will ſoon prepare war againſt you, though they have given you the name of Chriſtians by ſprinkling a little water upon you when you were children, and knew not what they did, and this for filthy lucres ſake; they fed you with the name of Chriſtians, but are wholly out of the nature themſelves; for the true nature and life of a Chriſtian is <hi>pure, peaceable, and eaſie to be intreated, not ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring evill for evill, but alwayes overcoming evil with good, doing unto all men, as they would all men ſhould do unto them;</hi> which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture they manifeſtly ſhew they are out of, <hi>By their fruits</hi> (which is the <hi>Mark,</hi>) Chriſt ſaid, <hi>ye ſhall know them:</hi> For it is very evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that none of them will be put into Priſon for any thing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to Religion, but they will cauſe others to be impriſoned, which thing Chriſtians never did, for their <hi>weapons were not carnal, but ſpiritual, and mighty through God, to the pulling down of the ſtrong holds of the kingdome of the man of ſin; neither did they wreſtle with fleſh and blood, but with Principalities and Powers, and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al wickedneſſe in High places, which captivate the creature.</hi> This was the Chriſtians warfare, which the Pope and all his Adherents are out of, who ſwear men to deſtroy Creatures as long as they
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:171156:16"/>live, contrary to Chriſt, <hi>who came not to deſtroy mens lives, but to ſave them,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all;</hi> but the Pope as I ſaid contrary to this, ſwears men to deſtroy creatures as long as they live, and to make away with fleſh and blood with carnal weapons; <hi>But they who ſmite with the ſword, ſhall be ſmitten with the ſword; and as they have loved blood, blood ſhall they have to drink;</hi> and ſo much the more, becauſe they have done it under the pretence of Religion, and of the defending of the true Church and Faith, which needeth not a carnal weapon to defend it; for the true Church <hi>is in God,</hi> therefore the gates of Hell cannot prevail againſt it, let them be open never ſo wide; and likewiſe the true Faith of Gods Elect, gives victory over Sin, Hell, Death and the Grave, and needeth not a Defendor, but is able to defend it ſelf, and conquer all the powers of darkneſſe which ariſeth up againſt it; ſo it plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeareth they have not the true Faith and Church, which muſt have a carnal weapon to defend it; and it being ſo, is the cauſe they cannot defend themſelves without an outward power to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold them, and if once that fail them, their kingdome would ſoon have an end, and the true Chriſtians kingdome ſhall flouriſh and proſper, for their kingdome and dominion is inviſible and without end, being redeemed out of Kingdomes, Tongues and Nations, to follow the Lamb through many tribulations, to enter into the everlaſting Kingdome of their Father which is without end; ſo this is the true Chriſtians life, ſtate and warfare to ſuffer perſecution, pray for enemies, and to do good to them which hate them, and ever ready to lay down his life for his vileſt enemies, and freely forgive, as he deſireth God his Father to forgive him, and out of this life I teſtifie there is no ſalvation; therefore read and conſider, a name will never ſave you without the nature, and this nature you can never witneſs except you follow Chriſt Jeſus through the Regeneration; for until the new birth come to be witneſſed, and the new creature known, that is renewed according to the likeneſs of him that created him; for neither Circumciſion availeth, nor uncircumciſion, <hi>but a new creature;</hi> there is but thoſe two bare rule in man, even <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel,</hi> the one a Murderer, the other a ſufferer, for which cauſe the ſacrifice of the one was accepted, and not the other, though they both offered of the good, yet <hi>Cain</hi> not being in the good, was not accepted, neither is any in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:171156:16"/>that nature unto this day accepted, for the Sacrifice of the wicked is an abomination to the Lord; therefore ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Except your righteouſneſs exceed the righteouſneſs of the</hi> Scribes <hi>and</hi> Phariſees, <hi>you ſhall in no wife enter into the Kingdome of God,</hi> Math. 5.20. Mark that, and conſider what their righteouſneſs ſtood in, even in the ſame that yours doth to this day, even in meats and drinks, and in the obſervation of dayes and times, new Moons and Sabbaths, and ſtand praying in the ſtreets, as I have ſeen ſome of you do, and that before Images: Therefore ceaſe from thoſe dead works that you may come to worſhip and ſerve the living God in ſpirit and truth, for ſuch only he ſeeketh to worſhip him. And again, Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Except a man be born again, he cannot ſee the Kingdom of God,</hi> Joh. 3. which is certain and true: So all people upon the face of the whole earth may prove themſelves by it, whether they be in the Kingdome, yea or nay, for no unclean thing can enter there, becauſe it is the holy habitation of the glorious God of all power.</p>
            <p>So be no longer deceived by the deceivers, but ſearch, try, and prove your ſelves, <hi>If Chriſt be not in you, ye are Reprobates,</hi> 2 Cor. 13.1. Profeſs what you will, droſs and reprobate ſilver ſhall ye be called, except ye repent, and ceaſe from this grievous Idolatry and will-Worſhip, Prieſts and People, without reſpect of perſons. Therefore whilſt you have a little time prize and lay it to heart before it be too late, for your Idolatry much exceedeth that of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> much leſs your righteouſneſſe: Therefore lay it to heart before things which belong to your eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal peace be hid from your eyes, and you be left to periſh eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Conſider, it is a dreadfull thing to fall into the hands of the living God; and if you ſlight this the day of your viſitation, ye ſhall in no wiſe eſcape them, but ſhall feel them in dreadful venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and judgment, which will be too heavy for you to bear; and in the day which is nigh at hand, you ſhall cry to the rocks and mountains to fall upon you, to cover you from the wrath of him who hath long born with you like a Lamb, checking and reproving you for evill by his pure light in your Conſciences, which if ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to hear and obey, you will feel him alſo as a Lion, before whom you ſhall never be able to flee, but by his dreadful wrath will you be conſumed; and all they who have executed judgment without
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:171156:17"/>mercy, ſhall have the ſame rendred into their own boſomes, for God is no reſpecter of perſons. And dreadful is that day which is dawning over your heads, wherein the hearts of every one ſhall be made manifeſt, and accordingly ſhall they receive at the hand of the Lord, and not according to names, habits, or titles. Theſe are true and faithful ſayings which ſhall ſhortly come to paſs; therefore bleſſed is he which is found waiting, that he may not be found eating and drinking with the drunken, nor ſmiting his fellow ſervant, for an account muſt every one give of their talents: Woe will be to the ſlothful and unfaithful ſervant when his Lord ſhall reckon with him; for every one of you have received a talent and gift from God to improve, and every particular of you ſhall be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to an account for it, how you have made uſe of the Lords mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: Read the portion of him who hid his Lords money in the earth, <hi>Math.</hi> 25.30. for it will aſſuredly be yours if ye do the like, even <hi>to be caſt into utter darkneſs, where ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi> If any ſhall ſay, have I a talent given me to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove, ſeeing I was never told ſo by any of my Teachers, which have been many a one, upon whom I have beſtowed a great part of my ſubſtance? yea, thou haſt a talent given thee of God, yet I do believe not any of the Teachers or Hireling Prieſts could tell thee or any ſo; but of a truth, a talent both thee and all men have, which is given them of God to improve, which talent is the Light wherewith Chriſt hath enlightned all men, which Light ſhineth in the Conſciences of all men, and teſtifieth againſt all the deeds of darkneſs, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. <hi>This is the grace of God unto ſalvation, which hath appeared unto all men, which taught the Saints to deny all ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, and to live ſoberly and righteouſly in this preſent evil world;</hi> which is the true improvement of it, and to that end it is given; and becauſe it is given and hath appeared to all men, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhall all men be left without excuſe in the day of account, and to plead ignorance will ſtand you in no ſtead in that day: Chriſt Jeſus ſaith <hi>The Kingdome of Heaven is within you,</hi> ſpeaking unto the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> yet they were not in the Kingdome, for if they had, <hi>they would not have crucified the Lord of glory.</hi> But this is a Miſtery to this dark Generation; for Chriſt compared the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven unto a <hi>grain of Muſtard-Seed;</hi> and alſo unto a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle leaven which a Woman took and hid in Meal, and it leavened
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:171156:17"/>the whole lump; therefore bleſſed and happy will they be, who come to know this leaven in themſelves, that ſo they may be leavened into its own holy pure nature, for the ſeed of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is in every one, though every one be not in it, yet it is there as a grain of Muſtard ſeed, yet where it takes root and grows, it becomes the biggeſt amongſt all the plants, and ſo co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereth the whole earth in man. Read the Parable and conſider, how the ſower went forth to ſow; he ſowed upon all ſorts of ground, but it was onely the good ground where it proſpered and tooke root downward, and brough forth fruit upward, <hi>ſome thirty, ſome ſixty, and ſome an hundred fold;</hi> this is the true increaſe of the talent and gift of God; let him that readeth underſtand that his ſoul may live, for untill this be read, felt, and underſtood, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe what you will, the ſoul lieth in death and miſery; therefore ye muſt diligently ſearch and ſeek this ſeed in the field, which is in the World in you, where this precious Pearl lyeth hid, that ye may be as the wiſe Merchant-man, who ſold all to purchaſe it, ſo muſt ye if it ever comes to be yours, yea, you muſt dig deep to find it, for it lyeth under all the mountaines of ſin, oppreſſed like a Cart which is laden with ſheaves in you, for the field is in you though wide, for the field is in the World which is in your hearts, and when the precious ſeed is grown, watch and wait leaſt the birds of the aire bereave you of it, or elſe the enemy ſow his evill ſeed in your ground, and ſo choak the good ſeed and plant of God, ſo that it cannot grow nor proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; for Friends, it is truly ſo, that <hi>ſtraight is the way which leadeth to life, and few there be that find it, but broad is the way that leadeth to deſtruction, and many there be which goe in thereat,</hi> for it is the way of ſin, but the other holineſſe and purity, <hi>without which no man ſhall ſee the Lord,</hi> as the Scripture ſaith, for it is the onely thing which ſhall ſtand in ſtead in the day of account: but woe will be unto them which then are, or ſhall be found co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and not with the Holy Spirit of God; all other coverings will be to ſhort to cover or ſave them from the dreadful woe and vengeance which is ready to come upon the inhabitants of the earth; for the Lord hath determined to bring Judgement upon the earth, that the inhabitants thereof may learn righteouſneſſe, for it is not to be found amongſt men, but every one is ſeeking
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:171156:18"/>his own way, ſeeking and ſtriving to exalt his own horn by op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion and deceit; but the Lord will rebuke many becauſe of theſe things, for oppreſſion ſhall ceaſe amongſt men, and the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſor ſhall ſurely be trodden under foot, and the meek of the earth ſhall have the dominion for evermore, which is the mind and purpoſe of the Lord of heaven and earth, therefore it ſhall ſurely come to paſſe, and woe will be to them who do ariſe to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Lord in this moſt glorious work, for they ſhall be beaten to powder, for the potſherds may ſtrive with potſherds, yet in vain will it be to ſtrive againſt the Lord, and his Holy Anoynted, who is come and coming to take the Kingdome, whoſe right it is for ever and ever, for all the Kingdomes of the World ſhall become the Kingdomes of the glorious Son of God: Therefore oh! ye inhabitants of the earth prepare to meet the Lord, and be ye warned that ye joyn not with the power of the oppreſſor, whom God is purpoſing to overturn, and chain down for ever, leaſt you periſh with him. This from the Lord God of heaven and earth is a warning to you all, that ye may be warned and left without excuſe, when the day ſhall come upon you which is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy dawned, and haſtens apace to ſhine in its glory, whereby all the works of darkneſſe ſhall be diſcovered, and made manifeſt, though never ſo ſecretly hid, as hath been already ſaid. It is high time for you to awake out of the deep ſleep of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, which you have been caſt into by the Magicians of <hi>Egypt,</hi> who have long kept your poor ſouls in ſpiritual bondage and ſlave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry through their deceit and lyes, for their own profit and lucre, of which they ſtrive to caſt a miſt before your eyes, telling you of the body of Chriſt, and inſtead of which they make you wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the works of your own hands, which will and doe periſh with the uſing, which the body of Chriſt can never doe inaſmuch as it is incorruptible, neither did or could ſee corruption; yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, your Prieſts have ſo far bewitched you, as that you your ſelves commonly confeſſe, that though they be never ſo wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet in the ſpeaking of ſo many words, they make the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible bread the very body of Chriſt; and ye are ſo far inchanted with this lye, inſomuch that if all within your Dominions do not fall down before this piece of bread and worſhip, you are ready to murder them; by which means your fruits ſhew you are in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:171156:18"/>the ſpirit of murther and envy, envying thoſe which will not own your lye and blaſphemy, calling earthly bread the Lords body, which is held in and by the hands of corruptible men, as you your ſelves are ready to ſay; the Lords ſoul abhors theſe things, for they are an abominable abomination before him: Conſider and lay it to heart, can the words that proceed out of the mouth of a ſinful man make any thing incorruptible? nay they cannot, ſeeing it is evident that out of one fountain ſalt water and ſweet cannot be had, <hi>neither can a bad tree bring forth good fruit,</hi> as ſaith Chriſt, neither can your deceivable Prieſts, who thus deceive you, doe any ſuch thing as they tell you of, neither have they any place in the holy Scripture which ſpeaks of any ſuch practices as thoſe which they deceive you with, that is, that men ſhould take a piece of bread, and ſay ſuch and ſuch words over it, that then it ſhould become the body of Chriſt, and that men ſhould fall down and proſtrate themſelves before it; nay they cannot cauſe bread to be converted into the body of Chriſt, neither can they convert the body of Chriſt into bread, let them ſpeak what, or as many words as they can over it: And thus they keep you in bondage as much as in them lyes, leaſt you ſhould ſearch and find out their deceit, and alſo from the reading of the Scriptures, leaſt their wickedneſſe ſhould be manifeſtly diſcovered, though Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Search the Scriptures for they teſtifie of me;</hi> but the Pope and his Prieſts forbid you to read them, which ſheweth that they are not of his mind, who would that all ſhould come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the truth and be ſaved, and not to keep people in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; for in the Scriptures it is recorded that the <hi>Bereans</hi> were more noble than others, becauſe that after they had heard the truth declared they went home and ſearched the Scriptures to ſee whether thoſe things were ſo, or no, yea or nay, you may ſee they were commended for ſo doing, and not forbidden, as your Prieſts doe; and the Apoſtles did bid <hi>try all things, and hold fast that which is good,</hi> which is far from forbidding any tryal in, and for truth; many of your own regular Prieſts will ſay them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that they are forbidden to diſpute: You may eaſily be kept in blindneſſe and darkneſſe, when many of your own teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers themſelves are not permitted to vindicate their own practiſes and works which they make you thus adore.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:171156:19"/>
            <p> Surely it is high time for you to ponder your wayes, for if you will wilfully continue to follow your blind guides, who dare not appear openly to vindicate their own way, as manifeſtly appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, ye will utterly fall into the pit of utter darkneſſe, both you and them together, out of which there is no recovery. I my ſelf have been a Priſoner in <hi>Bourg de Ault,</hi> for ſpeaking to a cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Prieſts, deſiring them that I might have the liberty either in publick Market place, or ſome other convenient place, where the people might hear, and I ſhould prove what I ſaid to them to be the truth of God; but ſeeing they denyed me that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an liberty, this I publiſh amongſt you; the truth of what here is written, I proffer'd to ſeal with my life, for I did proffer them my body to do with it what they had power; the ſame I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired of the Judg which had me in examination, yet it would not be granted me, yea, the two ſaid Prieſts did take two oaths againſt me, yet would not ſtay for to hear me ſpeak, but haſted away, though deſired, and ſome of the people did expect it; and this proves their works to be the works of darkneſſe, and not of the light, for <hi>he which doth good cometh to the light, that his works might be made manifest,</hi> that they are wrought in God; but they whoſe works are wrought in the dark <hi>hate the light, neither will they come to the light, becauſe their deeds are evill.</hi> So that by their fruits we know them, as Chriſt ſaid, who is the bread of life, which is inviſible, and nouriſheth the inviſible Soul, <hi>this is the true bread which came down from Heaven, and whoſoever feedeth thereon ſhall never dye,</hi> and except you come to eat of this his fleſh, and drink of his blood ye have no life in you, for it is incorruptible: And though he took bread and brake it to his diſciples the night before he was offered up, and ſaid, <hi>Take, eat, this is my body,</hi> he did not really give them his body, though he bid them break bread in remembrance of him untill he came; Mark, they were but to doe it untill he came, which ſhewed plainly the natural bread was not him, even whilſt it was in his own hand, but a figure of him, for as it was diſtributed amongſt them, ſo was his life; and that they were to do in remembrance untill his holy life deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon them again, which they did witneſſe not many dayes after at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and they had not need of any thing to put them in mind of him, for he lived and reigned really in them, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:171156:19"/>the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>it ſhewed the Lords death until he came,</hi> which ſaying was a glorious truth of God, for it brought them out of all viſibles, ſhewing that the inviſible light was to reign in them, for he reproved many of them who had gotten ſo into the breaking of bread, that they eat and drank until they were drunk, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> which the Lords body would not have done, yet their bread and wine had as much vertue in it as yours can have: But of theſe things we who are called <hi>Quakers,</hi> we would bring your teachers to open trial, to ſee whether it hath more vertue in it after conſecration as ye call it, then before the Prieſt hath ſpoken ſome of the words of Chriſt over the bread, for it is not unknown that the Devil did take the words of Scripture to tempt the Son of God with, therefore his children may in like manner ſpeak them, &amp; deceive the ſons of men with them: So that if they have any vertue in them, let them come forth in like manner, as hath been propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed unto them, (to wit) if their bread after conſecration, hath more vertue in it then other bread hath, let them ſhew it by the tryal of it, by putting it with other bread, and we and they ſhall ſee to the keeping of it, and if the one doe not corrupt as well as the other, then it will appear there is more vertue in it; but on the contrary, if they both corrupt, then may ye ſee your teachers to be Deceivers, and that ye are fed with a lye, for the body of Chriſt cannot corrupt, neither did it ever ſee corruption in that nature, for it is incorruptible and ſpiritual. Truly people this concerns you much to look into, ſeeing you are thus taught and deluded, <hi>for the Soul which ſinneth ſhall dye,</hi> and it will be a folly for any one of you for to ſay in the dreadful day of account, <hi>Our Fathers have eaten ſowre grapes, and our teeth are ſet on edge;</hi> pleading antiquity will not ſerve your turns, though I know God hath forborn you in theſe abominable abominations and Idolatry, even worſhipping of pieces of Bread, Stocks, and Stones, the one you ſay is the very body of Chriſt, and the other his likeneſſe, and all a lye, and hath and will be reproved and made manifeſt, and will get further to the utter overthrow of it all, for the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſt can no more be made by any, no more then bread naturall can be converted into his body by any, ſeeing <hi>he is the expreſſe Image of his Father,</hi> and never bare any other, But ſay you generally it puts us in mind, which plainly ſhews that ye are of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:171156:20"/>thoſe who forget God; <hi>David</hi> ſaid, <hi>The wicked ſhould be turned into Hell, and all who forget God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider you who ſay you muſt have a dead Image to put you in mind of the living Chriſt, and alſo this ſheweth that ye have not the mind of Chriſt, as the Chriſtians had. Friends, in this the day of tryal you are found bare, naked and miſerable; therefore be warned, that you may all come to the Light, which is the dore, the way, the truth and the life, <hi>and no man can come to the Father, but by him,</hi> (even Chriſt Jeſus) <hi>who is the Light of the world, which enlightneth every man that cometh into the world,</hi> who is the only dore and way to God, and whoſoever goeth about to enter any other way, but by the Light, the ſame <hi>is a thief and a robber,</hi> as ſaith Chriſt, who is the Covenant of God to all mankind up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the face of the whole earth; <hi>and to this end came he into the world, that through him all might believe, and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever doth, out of his belly ſhall flow a River of living water,</hi> which is beyond all Naturals, which can alone be ſeen, handled, and taſted by the Spiritual; and whoſoever comes to be ſenſible of its pure ſtreams, will for ever delight to drink thereof, there being ſatisfaction therein only, which my ſoul knoweth right well, therefore am I drawn forth in the ſame, wherewith the Lord hath loved me, to invite many that they may eat and drink that which my Father hath provided for many, even for thoſe who are ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and ſtraglers in the high-wayes and hedges, for a banquet hath my God prepared, and hath, and is ſending out his Servants to invite and bid many, but many already have made their excuſes, by which means they are not found worthy: Therefore ye which are ſtraglers, come away, even ye who are as much ſtrangers as any; fear not, faint not, ye ſhall have your penny as well as thoſe who laboured in the heat of the day: I ſay, come away, a feaſt of fat things is prepared for you, even a goodly heritage which flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with Milk and Honey, there is large poſſeſſions therein my friends for you, and if ye be willing and obedient, ye ſhall eat of the good thereof; yea, <hi>In my Fathers houſe are many Manſions,</hi> and if it were not ſo, I ſhould not ſay it; but as my ſoul hath rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fed thereof, ſo I would all ſhould come away, and partake with me of the ſame; I am truly filled with love, ever as a veſſel which is filled with new Wine, even to all the whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:171156:20"/>of God, and would if it were poſſible perſwade all the Sons of men to come away, for the Bride hath made her ſelf ready, and the Marriage-Chamber is prepared, <hi>And the voice of the Spirit ſaith come, yea all that will, come freely;</hi> ſee therefore that you have your Lamps trimmed, all to the Light, that ye may not be of the number of the <hi>fooliſh Virgins,</hi> and ſo miſs your entrance into the Marriage-Chamber, for though the door may be freely open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet it will not be alwayes, therefore <hi>Bleſſed are they who are found watching,</hi> that when the cry of the Bridegroom cometh they may enter, for they ſhall enjoy the joy of their Lord, and there will be no more cauſe of weeping, becauſe the Bridegroom will be alwayes with them, but they which are fooliſh, ſhall be ſhut out among the Dogs and Sorcerers; therefore be ye warned, that ye may be partakers of peace, reſt, and joy for evermore, and think not any thing too dear to part from, for the <hi>price of the Mark of the High Calling, which is in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> that is ſet before you; for ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall forſake father and mother, wife or children, houſe or land, for my ſake, ſhall receive an hundred fold in this world, and in the world to come life everlaſting.</hi> And truly friends, I tell you by true experience, that the ſufferings of this world is not to be compared to the joy which is and ſhall be revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in us; and though many may ſpeak evil of you, and revile you, becauſe ye run not into the ſame exceſs of riot as before, heed it not, if you receive Chriſt ye ſhall have <hi>power to become the Sons of God,</hi> which will be greater riches than ye can looſe in this world, being made witneſſes of the birth which is not of man, nor by man, but of God: I ſay this will bear you over all the reproaches of the wicked one, and this ſtate you will come to know, by taking up the dayly Croſs, and following of Chriſt, for he that will be his Diſciple muſt ſo do in reallity and in truth, which Croſs is not a piece of Wood or Stone, neither will you need any ſuch thing to put you in mind of God, or Chriſt, but the Croſs ye will witneſs to be the power of God unto ſalvation, if you believe; for <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>God forbid that he ſhould glory in any thing, but the Croſs of Chriſt, whereby he was crucified unto the world, and the world unto him;</hi> ſo as you come to witneſſe the true Croſs, and to bear it dayly, you will come to witneſſe the ſame thing, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which, all your profeſſion will be vain; ſo as you come to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:171156:21"/>dwell, abide, and walk here, you will come to know what the true Baptiſme of Chriſt Jeſus is, <hi>which is the Fire and the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> without which you cannot witneſſe the body of ſin put off, and except you do witneſſe this, ye are far from Chriſts life, which makes a true Chriſtian, for it is not only the waſhing away of the filth of the fleſh, but the anſwer of a good Conſcience towards God: And this is the onely Baptiſme which muſt be witneſſed by all, before they come to a Chriſtians life, for the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>There was but one Baptiſme, which is the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of the Spirit,</hi> for <hi>John</hi> ſaid, <hi>He was to decreaſe, but Chriſt was to encreaſe;</hi> for his Baptiſme was but a figure of the true Baptiſme, for Chriſt came through all Figures having the Subſtance and the Life in himſelf; ſo they who come to this only true Baptiſme, which is onely needful to ſalvation, they come to receive the gift of the Holy Ghoſt, for they who knew no other but <hi>Johns</hi> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, they knew not whether there was a Holy Ghoſt or no; therefore it is ſaid concerning <hi>Apollo, That he onely knew Johns Baptiſme,</hi> and that <hi>Priſcilla</hi> and <hi>Aquilla miniſtred unto him, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed him in the way of God more perfectly:</hi> Therefore be ye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in this matter, and be ye no longer deceived with a name and ſhadow, but come to the ſubſtance, that your ſouls may live for ever, ſo will bleſſing and mercy follow you all your dayes, and happy ſhall you be in the end thereof; though men may perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute and revile you, matter it not, for ſo they did to Chriſt Jeſus, and the Holy Prophets before you, and remember <hi>The Servant is not greater than his Lord,</hi> And the Saints of old, <hi>who wandred up and down cloathed with skins, and wandred up and down in dens and holes of the earth, of whom the world was not worthy.</hi> I ſay all who deſire eternal life, take them for an example, in ſufferings, and patience, and your names will be written in the Book of Life with them, even amongſt thoſe who are ſanctified, <hi>who loved not their lives unto the death;</hi> by which means they came to be crowned with immortal Glory, even to live and reign with the Lamb upon Mount <hi>Sion</hi> for ever, which is not to be compared with all the treaſures of <hi>Egypt,</hi> the Gold of <hi>Ophir,</hi> or <hi>Onix</hi> ſtones. And it being ſo that nothing availeth any but a new creature, What do you think will all your Croſſes
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:171156:21"/>avail you, with your Beads and Reliques of dead men and womens bones, with your Proceſſioning and counterfeit Faſts, Pardons for ſins from the Pope, and the like ſtuffe, as your vain repetition of other mens words in your prayers, and giving your means to build great Monaſteries for men to be kept up a fatting, like ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Swine, living idlely upon the Creation of God, and likewiſe women, who are as wanton as Beaſts, kept and fed there? I ſay what will all theſe avail you and them? but adde to your condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, ſeeing the ground and root of the old man ſtands whole in you, in which nature all your works is not accepted with God, <hi>who is a Spirit, and muſt be worſhipped in Spirit and in Truth, and ſuch onely he ſeeketh to worſhip him.</hi> So it is no more at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> or at this, or that place or houſe, where God is worſhipped, neither doth he dwell in Temples made with hands, for he hath no need of theſe things, nor yet ſerved with corrupt mens hands; and for bearing witneſſe unto this, <hi>Steven</hi> was ſtoned, whoſe name ye adore, but he is a witneſſe againſt you and your practices herein, for whileſt you are obſerving the things before named, you are but in the nature which ſtoned him for witneſſing the end of all outward Ceremonies, even of thoſe which were true Figures and Types of the Subſtance which was to come; and if them things were witneſſed againſt, as being unprofitable, the Subſtance being come, which was Chriſt, may not yours much more be witneſſed againſt, as being wholly unprofitable, <hi>which never were comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, nor types of any thing,</hi> but of the miſtery of iniquity, being things of your own inventing, through which you are wholly lead from the knowledge of God, being meer vanities and inventions of mens hands? ſo as you ſow to your ſelves vanity, you will have nothing elſe to reap in the end; for the true Chriſtians came to witneſſe their bodies to be the Temples of God, through the Spirit which dwelt in them, which was the new creature, which onely availeth; for ſaith God, <hi>I will be in them, and walk in them, and I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people:</hi> This is Gods Covenant with his people, which Covenant ſtandeth onely with the <hi>New Creature.</hi> And again, ſaith he, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto this man will I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, unto him who is of an humble and a contrite ſpirit, and trembleth at my word.</hi> And untill you come to witneſſe this ſtate, God
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:171156:22"/>Allmighty hath no regard, as to accept any thing at your hands; therefore <hi>prize</hi> the new-birth, and ſeek vigilantly after it, that ye might have acceptance with God, and have an entrance into his holy Kingdome, <hi>for no unclean thing can enter therein;</hi> therefore there is a neceſſity of putting off the old man with his deeds, that a new may be witneſſed, <hi>who after God is created in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe;</hi> and where this comes to be witneſſed, the mind is renewed, and <hi>all old things are paſſed away, and all things become new,</hi> which is the onely and alone bleſſed ſtate, and this onely availeth, and ſtandeth inſtead in the day of tryal, when the hearts of all ſhall be made manifeſt, and the ſecrets of all judged by Jeſus Chriſt, according to the everlaſting Goſpel of life, truth and power; for God hath verily appointed a day wherein he will ſurely judge the world, though many ſay and think that he delay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his coming, not conſidering that his long-ſuffering and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance ſhould lead them to repentance; but of a truth he is not ſlack, as ſome men count ſlackneſs concerning his coming, though many ſay or think he delayeth, but his day ſhall overtake them as a thief in the night, even in a time when they look not for him. Remember the old world, they were eating and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, marrying and giving in marriage, but the juſt man preached repentance unto them, untill the overflowing ſtroak of Gods wrath ſwept them away; and alſo juſt <hi>Lot,</hi> whoſe <hi>righteous ſoul was dayly grieved with the unrighteous converſation of the wicked Sodomites,</hi> who would not be warned, but when they were told of the evil which came upon them, they ſlighted the meſſage, and ſought evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to entreat the Meſſengers; therefore God made them exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples for Generations to come, yea even to this Generation, whoſe meaſure of iniquity ſurpaſſeth theirs; and do you think God will ſpare you any more than he did them? nay, he will not, for God bore untill they had filled up the meaſure of their iniquity, as he doth yours now, whoſe meaſure aboundeth more than any that ever yet went before you, in luſt, pride and envy, deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, idleneſs, and fulneſs of bread, which were the ſins of <hi>Sodome,</hi> which crucified the Juſt, even as you do this day, dayly and hour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for it is in ſpirituall <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> where the Lord of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is crucified; <hi>Let him that readeth underſtand;</hi> you need not a Stock or a Stone to put you in mind, or the Image of a dead man
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:171156:22"/>to put you in mind how the Juſt ſuffered ſixteen hundred years agoe, if ye rightly conſidered; for it is your wicked converſation which crucifieth him amongſt you, ſo that ye are as truly guilty of his blood, as the <hi>Jews</hi> were, though you keep them in oppreſſion. And theſe my words ye ſhall eternally witneſs if ever you come to a true converſion and fear of God, for ſuch ſhall come to <hi>ſee him whom they have pierced, and mourn over him as a man mourneth over his only begotten ſon,</hi> as ſaith the Prophet. Therefore I declare un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you all, there is not a man but is, or hath been guilty of the blood of the Son of God, for he is the Lamb <hi>ſlain from the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World,</hi> and <hi>The whole world lyeth in wickedneſs,</hi> as alſo ſaith the Apoſtle; and it is the wickedneſs which ſlayeth the Lamb, as it is written, <hi>The juſt ſuffereth by the unjuſt:</hi> Therefore repent that ye may find mercy, or elſe his blood will be too heavy for you to bear; and it will not juſtifie you to call him Lord, Lord, while the Devil reigns as Lord in you; neither to call God Father, while your works teſtifie openly to your faces, that <hi>you are of your father the Devil, whoſe works ye do;</hi> for if ye were the children of God, ye would do the works of God, which are all righteous, holy, and true; but that birth ye never yet knew, for <hi>they who are born of God ſinneth not,</hi> as ſaith the Scripture. And your praying to <hi>Mary</hi> will not ſerve your turns, for it is only thoſe who do the will of the Father which are accepted of him, for ſaith Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>He that doth the will of my Father, the ſame is my Mother, Siſter, and Brother:</hi> Mark that, and conſider what your invoking the Saints with vain Repetitions will availe you, but only adde to your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, for Chriſt ſaith, <hi>for every idle word a man ſhall give an account at the day of Judgment;</hi> for though ye could ſay in that dreadful day, <hi>Lord, we have propheſied in thy name, and in thy name have we caſt out Devils,</hi> yet conſider the anſwer, <hi>Depart from me ye curſed workers of iniquity, I know you not;</hi> the Lake is prepared for all ſuch; therefore conſider: <hi>I was ſick, and ye viſited me not; naked, and ye cloathed me not; I was an hungry, and ye gave me no bread;</hi> and if the portion of ſuch be ſo dreadfull, what will yours be who have caſt into priſon? even woe and vengeance for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. Therefore beware what you do, and conſider, the true Chriſtians never impriſoned any, which may be a warning and an example unto you to follow, that you may no further become guilty
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:171156:23"/>of the blood of the innocent, for God will aſſuredly try you with theſe things: Therefore a warning from the God of love is this unto you, which if ye reject, dreadfull will be the end thereof; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in time conſider: This word is often in my heart towards you, that you may lay it to heart and conſider, for it is becauſe of ſin the Land mourneth, and becauſe of ſin wrath hath ever come upon the ſons of men, and think not that ye ſhall be exempted more then others, ſeeing your abomination exceedeth all the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt Generations; for God ſpared the old inhabitants of the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> no longer, then till the meaſure of their iniquity was filled up: And by it do you take warning, and turn to the Lord by true repentance, leaſt the Angel of his wrath ſmite you, which he is ſending forth, whoſe ſword is already drawn to ſmite the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the earth: Therefore except ye turn to God ſpeedily, and bring forth fruits meet for repentance and amendment of life, the Sword ſhall be ſheathed in your bowels, for God reſpecteth not the manner nor the perſon of any man, nation or people, but all in the particular ſhall receive according as they have done, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good or evil, if they ſlight the day of their viſitation which is freely tendered unto them, which is Gods endleſs mercy and goodneſs, after ſo long forbearance with them; therefore beware leaſt this love be turned to your condemnation, by reaſon of the hardneſs of your hearts, and there be no place found for repentance, though with <hi>Eſau</hi> you may ſeek it with tears, for he had a birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, but he ſold it for a meſs of pottage, a thing of nought; ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you is life and death ſet, good and evil, chuſe you whether one or other; I ſhall be clear of your blood if ye periſh, who have tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly warned you, as I was moved of the Lord, even to you people of this nation, of what ſort or degree ſoever, and ye ſhall one day re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, though at preſent ye may ſlight it, and count it as idle talk, yet ye are warned in an acceptable time, and in a day of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if ſo be ye accept it. And alſo your obſerving of dayes and times will not excuſe you, as I have already ſaid, for the Apoſtle ſaid he was afraid of thoſe which were in thoſe things, <hi>leaſt he had beſtowed labour in vain upon them;</hi> for his labour was to bring peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple out of the obſervation of dayes and times, up to him who was before time was, who is God over all bleſſed for evermore: And they who are not come hither, are in the beggerly Elements and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:171156:23"/>Rudiments which fadeth away, for, ſaith <hi>Paul, Let no man judg you in meats, or drinks, or new Moons, or the Sabbath dayes, which things are but ſhadows of good things to come;</hi> mark how far the Pope and his Miniſters are from this doctrine, who commandeth dayes and times to be obſerved, which are neither Types nor Shadows of things to come, nor of any thing promiſed, but are their own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions; ſo that ye are taught for doctrine the Commandments of men, and for the peoples Fear towards God, is taught the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of men: Therefore ceaſe in time from them, for wrath is kindled againſt them and their works, who thus lead the people in groſs ignorance, even to have as many Advocates as there are dayes in the year. And your dayes and times ye obſerve, were never commanded of God, nor his Servants, yea, the very day you call the Sabbath, is not the day which was commanded the <hi>Jewes,</hi> they being witneſſes againſt you in that thing, for it was the ſeaventh day that was commanded, but it is the firſt day they put you upon to keep, and inſtead of keeping it holy, according to the Commandment, it is commonly kept the prophaneſt of all the reſt, except your other dayes dedicated to dead men and women, as the Heathen do to the Sun and Moon, for in the ground there is no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between you in this particular; and your keeping theſe days, as you pretend at beſt, is in honour to ſuch &amp; ſuch Saints, but ye are a ſhame to Saints, and the very name of Chriſtians is evill ſpoken of through ſuch means, for which cauſe the Lord will aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly plead with you, if ye repent not, for the day which all Saints are in, is perfect, pure, holy peace and reſt, of which the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> was a true Type, for ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>He that believeth is entered into reſt,</hi> and hath ceaſed from his own works, as God did from his, which Reſt is Chriſt the Saviour of the ſoul, and whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever comes to enter in will witneſs my words; and out of him there is nothing but grief and vexation of ſpirit; for <hi>in me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>ye ſhall have peace, but in the World trouble:</hi> Peace is the true Reſt, ſo where it reigneth in the heart the true reſt and Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath is known, and not until then can an holy day be witneſſed. Oh come all to the Light which reproveth for ſin in the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſo will you come to Chriſt, who is the only way and path of peace to all who believe; but to the diſobedient he is condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: And this ye ſhall witneſs whether ye will hear or forbear,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:171156:24"/>for it is the word of the Lord God to you, for if your hearts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn you, ye cannot have confidence towards God, for God is greater; but if your hearts be turned to the Light, they come to be purified, and then the peace of God which paſſeth all under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding will reign there, ſo will you come to have confidence to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, as ſaith the Scripture; for if the heart be ſmitten, it is becauſe of tranſgreſſion; and ſaith my God, <hi>There is no peace to the wicked,</hi> but woe and torment ſhall follow them for ever, though they may ſeek to avoyd it, through the curſed deluſion of the blind Prieſts, by giving them money for pardons, when ye have committed murder or ſome wicked act, and are judged in your ſelves, for by the Light of Chriſt Jeſus in your Conſciences are you judged; I ſay, to think to get eaſe ye run to the covetous, corrupt wicked men, and confeſs to them, giving them money for pardons for ſins, and money for ſaying of Maſſes, and the like; but know ye aſſuredly that the Lord God will not pardon you; <hi>except ye come to confeſs and forſake your ſins,</hi> ye will never find mercy at the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal ſeat of the righteous Judg of Heaven and Earth, neither you, nor your Confeſſors; therefore ceaſe from them, leaſt you and them periſh together, which will aſſuredly come to paſſe if ye continue in your ſtubbornneſs and gainſaying: Remember the dreadful end of <hi>Dathan, Abiram,</hi> and of <hi>Corah,</hi> who periſhed in their gainſaying, leaſt you come to the ſame end, which is unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverable for evermore: Let the word ever ſink down into your hearts, ſo may you remember the endleſs time of torments, which is prepared for the Devil and his Angels, even the man of ſin, <hi>who was a Lyar from the beginning:</hi> And do but try his Miniſters by this, and try if they preach not up ſin as long as life laſteth, and ſay that man cannot be free therefrom, nor put off the body of ſin while in this life, by which means they ſtrengthen the hands of the wicked, ſo that they cannot turn from their wickedneſs, by preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up their Maſters Kingdome for term of life, which thing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, the Devil knows he hath them ſure enough, becauſe it was the ſin unto death which the Apoſtle ſaid ſhould not be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for.</p>
            <p>So people, Conſider the miſerable captivity and bondage you are in, ſpending all the dayes of your lives in being taught by theſe Deceivers, and in the end you muſt die in your ſins, which is a
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:171156:24"/>deplorable ſtate, <hi>for the Wages of ſin is death,</hi> and <hi>as the Tree falls ſo it lyes,</hi> ſaith the Scripture, <hi>and every one ſhall receive according to the deeds done in the body,</hi> for <hi>his ſervants ye are to whom ye obey, whether of ſin unto death, or of righteouſneſſe unto eternall life:</hi> So read and conſider, and be no longer deceived; God will not be mocked, <hi>Such as you ſow, ſuch ſhall ye reap,</hi> and money cannot buy you an immortal poſſeſſion, neither can corruption purchaſe incorruption, as your wicked leaders make you in effect to believe.</p>
            <p>Thus hath the miſtery of Iniquity, and the man of ſin fully wrought and revealed, who by all deceiveableneſſe of unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe deceived the Nations, one after this manner, and another after that manner, but his ſubtile wiles hath wrought the deepeſt amongſt men under the name of Chriſtians, that thereby he might the eaſier deceive the hearts of the ſimple, who have any deſire in them after the true and living God, and for theſe his inſtruments in this work, he hath impoſed the moſt ſubtile and craftieſt men in all generations ſince the power of his working, thereby the more to amaze the people, in ſaying, are not theſe the learned men? are not theſe the Orthodox men? and if theſe do not know, how ſhould we know, who are illiterate and unlearned every way, and by this his deceiveable working hath he poſſeſſed the hearts of the people with a lye, <hi>for the wiſdome of the wiſe men of this world know not the things of God,</hi> neither can the naturall man diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the things of the Spirit, for they are ſpiritually diſcerned; therefore ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Ye ſee your Calling, Brethren, how that not many wiſe men after the fleſh, not many mighty, not many noble are called; for God hath choſen the fooliſh things of the world, to confound the wiſe; God hath choſen the weak things of the world, to confound the mighty; and baſe things of the world, and things which are deſpiſed hath God choſen, yea, and things which are not, to bring to nought things that are, that no fleſh might glory in his preſence; but of him are ye in Chriſt Jeſus, who of God hath made him unto us wiſdome, righteouſneſſe, ſanctification, and redemption,</hi> that according as it is written, <hi>he that glorieth let him glory in the Lord,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 26-31. yea, <hi>and God taketh the wiſe in their own craft, and turneth the wiſdome of the wiſe backward, becauſe the fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God is wiſer then men, and the wiſdome of man is fooliſhneſſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:171156:25"/>with God;</hi> and Chriſt Jeſus alſo ſaith, <hi>I thank thee Father, that thou haſt hid theſe things from the wiſe and prudent, and haſt revealed them unto babes and ſucklings:</hi> Mark, God hath even revealed his ſecrets unto babes and ſucklings, in which God doth perfect his praiſes, and this is marvelous in the eyes of many: And alſo the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <hi>God hath choſen the poor of this world rich in faith, and heirs of the Kingdome.</hi> Friends, this is far from the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Doctrine, who exalt learning above the Spirit of God, in whom is the candle of wiſdome, and in ſaying this I doe them no wrong, for it appeareth evidently every way; doe they not make uſe of a ſort of men, which they call <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Monks?</hi> whom they eſteeme the moſt, to go to and fro abroad in the Nations, and by their ſubtilty any way exalt their own horn, through which means much blood hath been ſhed, and grievous diſorders amongſt many hath been; their fruits and effects will be witneſſe enough for theſe things: This is far from the example of Chriſt Jeſus, who made choyce of ſimple poor Fiſher-men to ſend forth in his work, even ſuch who knew not the letter, as ſaith the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and the wiſdome of the <hi>Jews</hi> in thoſe dayes, had the ſimple hearted (who believed) in deriſion, eſteemed them accurſed becauſe they knew not the Law, <hi>and aſked if any of the Rulers did believe,</hi> for ye may ſee preaching of Chriſt was eſteemed a thing ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much below them, yet through the fooliſhneſs of this preaching, (as it was accounted of by the wiſdome of man,) it pleaſed the Lord to ſave many, for the Croſs of Chriſt was preached, which <hi>to the Jews was a ſtumbling block, and to the Greeks fooliſhneſſe,</hi> who ſought after wiſdome in thoſe dayes, <hi>but to every one that believed, it was the power of God unto ſalvation,</hi> as hath been ſaid, <hi>for he that will be truly wiſe unto ſalvation, must truly become a fool,</hi> (as ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that he may be made wiſe;</hi> and ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Except ye be converted, and become as little children, ye cannot enter into the Kingdome of God:</hi> And this was witneſſed by <hi>Paul,</hi> who according to the learning and wiſdome of this world, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed many in his generation, (who was brought up at the feet of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi>) <hi>yet accounted it but dung and droſſe, that he might win Chriſt, though according to the fleſh he might glory above many. Where is the wiſe? where is the diſputer? hath not God appointed the the fooliſh things to confound them?</hi> yea verily, and ſhall for ever.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:171156:25"/>
               <hi>The little ſtone which is cut out of the mountain without hands</hi> (which is ſpoken of in <hi>Daniel,</hi>) <hi>ſhall become a great mountain, and cover the whole earth,</hi> and bleſſed are they who ſhall fall upon it that they may be broken, for if it fall upon them it will grind them to powder be they never ſo mighty, or never ſo learned, and never ſo prudent, they ſhall never be able to ſtand before him. Therefore all people, ſubmit, and come under the banner of his love, which is ſtretched forth over your heads, for if you doe not, you muſt come under his iron rod, which will daſh you to pieces, for reign over all he muſt for ever and evermore, though <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> ſet themſelves in battel againſt him, yea, no weapon formed againſt him ſhall proſper, for their great grength ſhall be turned into confuſion for ever; the Lord God of Heaven and Earth hath determined it, whoſe will and purpoſe none ſhall be able to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent: though <hi>the Heathen may rage, and the people imagine a vain thing,</hi> yet all ſhall be in vain, for <hi>God will ſet his Son upon his holy hill of Sion,</hi> to reign over all for ever, whoſe right alone it is, and for his ſake he will rebuke Kings: Therefore bleſſed ſhall they be who reſiſt not his glorious coming; though Satan may have power a while to kill ſome of his followers, and caſt others into priſon, to the end that the hearts of many be tryed and made manifeſt, yet it ſhall be but for a ſeaſon, and the righteous their teſtimonies ſhall crown them for ever in the ſight of all their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies; and this glorious work ſhall not be carried on by ſword nor ſpear, but by my Spirit, ſaith the Lord, (that no fleſh might glory in his preſence) even with the Sword of the Spirit that proceedeth out of the mouth of the Lamb ſhall his enemies be overcome, and put to flight, and in his glorious power ſhall one chaſe a thouſand, and ten ſhall put Nations to flight; a people hath the Lord already raiſed and ſanctified for this work, before whom the uncircumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſhall never be able to ſtand againſt them in battel: the Lord hath made them his battle-Ax, to cut up the root of corruption, and deſtroy it for ever, that the glorious plant of incorruption may take root and grow, and ſpread over the whole earth for ever, to the praiſe and glory of the Eternal God of all glory, to whom all praiſe, honour, and glory belongeth, from all things, whether things above, or in the earth beneath, who will defend and make known his Tabernacle amongſt the ſons of men, and his name ſhall be
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:171156:26"/>dreadful in the earth, <hi>For he will eſtabliſh Judges as at the firſt, and Counſellors as at the beginning,</hi> which ſhall not judge for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, but in righteouſneſſe will they judge, without reſpect of perſons in the earth; and untill this be accompliſhed there ſhall be no peace in the earth, nor <hi>The will of God cannot be done in Earth, as it is in Heaven;</hi> though your Prieſts bid you ſay them words as Chriſt bid thoſe who had forſaken all to follow him, the which ſtate ye never yet came to witneſſe, as you and your Prieſts fruits make manifeſt, and bid you ſay that which they could never wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe themſelves, which will be their great condemnation, for none can call God <hi>Father, but they who are born of him,</hi> and ſuch only forgives enemies, as God forgives them, and not in word onely, but in deed and in truth; and whoſo ſaith, <hi>Father forgive us, as we forgive them which treſpaſs againſt us,</hi> are in a wofull condition, being in the contrary nature, biting and devouring one another; the Prieſts ſuing the People, and the People ſuing the Prieſts at Law, and thus ſuing one another, what forgiveneſs can you expect from God, who deſires this, that <hi>ye may be forgiven, as you forgive others?</hi> the holy will of God is far from being done in you, as it is in Heaven, who are fighters one with another, though ye call one another Chriſtians, and the like; thus you ask a thing to your own confuſion for ever.</p>
            <p>Oh be ye awakened and conſider theſe things, and repent, for of a truth juſt judgements will overtake you early, unawares, and all your talk of prayer will ſtand you in no ſtead, though you may ſay them your ſelves, or get others to ſay them for you, as you are inſtructed in <hi>Rome,</hi> as may be ſeen in a Book called <hi>Raris Sario,</hi> or <hi>Lacorene daela madonae,</hi> which is the common Book for the lay Peoples inſtructions in matter and manner of their Worſhip; was there ever ſuch abominable abomination as this, that a man may have another to do or ſay his task of Prayer, and it ſhall be all one as though he had done it himſelf? doth not this make it plainly appear that they are Miniſters of darkneſſe, and know not the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which maketh interceſſion for us, and knoweth our wants? Doth not the Apoſtle ſay, <hi>He will pray with the Spirit, and with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding;</hi> and again, <hi>Pray alwaies, and in every thing give thanks,</hi> yea, <hi>Pray alwayes without ceaſing.</hi> And you are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of this pure ſpirit of prayer and ſupplication, which is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:171156:26"/>of the Lord God unto his people, inſomuch that you muſt have a certain task of prayers, and that they may be ſaid by any other, and as well accepted as though you had ſaid them your ſelves, and in truth it is ſo, for neither of them both is accepted of God; this is ſuch groſs darkneſs as might be felt, and truly your task-maſters are more wicked than ever any in <hi>Egypt</hi> were, and are more unexcuſable, inasmuch as they profeſſe and pretend to be Chriſtians; think you that God accepteth theſe your vain Repetitions and Oblations? nay, they are a ſtink unto him, and an abomination unto him for ever; for it is onely the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices and prayers of a broken heart which God accepteth, even they who have clean hands, and pure hearts, onely ſuch he accepteth, and ſuch he will in no wiſe deſpiſe, but taketh dayly care of them, knowing their dayly wants and what they ſtand in need of before they ask, and doth alſo an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer their requeſts, <hi>becauſe the Spirit maketh interceſſion for them, in, and with ſighs and groans that cannot be uttered.</hi> The decree came forth at the beginning of <hi>Samuels</hi> ſupplications, and was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered while he was yet ſpeaking; many at this day witneſſe the ſame thing, <hi>Glory be unto the Lord for ever, who hath pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red forth according to his promiſe the true ſpirit of grace and ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon many, in and through which they are accepted of him in prayer;</hi> but there are ſuch the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> ſpeaks of, <hi>which ask and receive not, becauſe they ask amiſſe,</hi> even to ſpend it upon their luſt; and ſuch is your prayers, as plainly appeareth, for ye have no anſwer from God, for after ye have done all your task to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, which is laid upon you, yet muſt have Indulgences from men, and Pardons from men, which if you had anſwer from God and forgiveneſs, theſe things would appear unto you abominable and deteſtable; for after all your Pardons, you muſt give money to your Prieſt to be prayed for after you are dead, which ſheweth you have not yet received the remiſſion of your ſins in this life, in and through Chriſt Jeſus, who ſaith, <hi>Whatſoever ye ask in my name, it ſhall be given,</hi> whoſe Miniſters preached remiſſion of ſins in this life, through the man Chriſt Jeſus, and ſaid, <hi>His blood cleanſed from all unrighteouſneſſe, even theirs who did confeſſe their ſins and forſake them:</hi> And <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>Ye are not redeemed with corruptible things (from your vain converſation) as Gold, or Silver,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:171156:27"/>but by the blood of the Lamb.</hi> (Mark) here the Saints did witneſſe redemption from ſin in this life, for then was it that the Apoſtle did write unto them, and ſuch did not need a Purgatory to be purged in after they were dead, neither did there need money to be given for them upon any ſuch account, to get them out quickly from thence, as though prayers which are purchaſed by money could any way pacifie God, or with-hold the juſt judgement of God which is due for ſin: <hi>Surely</hi> (as ſaith the Prophet) <hi>they that ſeek after lying vanities, forſake their own mercies;</hi> for it would have hardly entred into the heart of any man that ſuch things ſhould be believed, for were it not that men were given over to believe a lye that they might be damned, becauſe they do not like to retain God in their knowledge, nor take heed to that of God which is manifeſt in them, which if they did, they would ſoon come out of this horrible deceit, into the true knowledge of his eternal power and God-head, for God would manifeſt it unto them.</p>
            <p>Oh People! ſeriouſly conſider, and read the Scriptures, and ſee if you can read a word of Purgatory, or that if ever men gave money to be prayed for after they were dead, or that if any ſought to give money to men for pardons for ſins, or whether any of the Apoſtles and Diſciples of Chriſt did appoint people a ſet manner of prayer, one part to ſuch a Saint, and another part to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and the like: Surely, if you are not wilfully bent to be enemies to God, and your own ſouls, and reſolved to periſh, you would certainly look unto theſe things, and be no longer deceived, for the arm of Gods everlaſting love is ſtretched out towards you, to draw you out of theſe miſerable deluſions, and his voyce calleth unto you; therefore <hi>whileſt it is called to day, harden not your hearts, as in the provocation;</hi> for if ye do, ye will ſurely periſh eternally, which is the Word of the Lord unto you all, whoſe bowels of pity and mercy is unto you; therefore repent, repent that ye may meet and receive the mercy, and be accepted of the Lord, for truly his pure Spirit hath long been grieved with you, and hath been oppreſſed, even as a Cart is laden with ſheaves, with your iniquities; therefore be warned, and repent.</p>
            <p>And from whence come all the abominable abominations and deluſions, but from the painted Harlot that rideth upon the Beaſt,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:171156:27"/>cloathed with Scarlet, with the Cup of fornication in her hand, by which you are made drunk, as not to diſcern her deviliſh witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft which ſhe deceives you with, to the end that ſhe may uphold her own pride, luſt, and wickedneſs, painting and decking her ſelf like <hi>Jezabel</hi> her mother, out of whoſe womb ſhe came, ſeeking and hunting continually after the Servants and Prophets of the true and living God to deſtroy them, while ſhe feedeth many hundred falſe ones at her Table, fed like ſo many pompered Beaſts at the Stall of the Staller, which ſhe maintains to miniſter to her Idols and Images, from which they can have no anſwer in the day of tryall, as it appeareth plainly, and will upon further tryal; therefore woe will be unto them which joyn with her to uphold her, <hi>for they ſhall periſh utterly with her for ever;</hi> and though ſhe hath pretended to forgive many, yet God will not forgive her; but as ſhe loveth blood, ſhe ſhall have blood to drink, yea, a double portion in her own bowels ſhall be rendred unto her, for the evil which ſhe hath done to others, <hi>The mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it,</hi> and the Dogs ſhall eat her fleſh, and none ſhall be able to deliver her out of the hand of the Allmighty, who hath determined her deſtruction, and ſealed the decree againſt her; and many hath the Lord already mounted in the Chariots of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to go forth againſt her, yea cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen men of valour and ſtrength, whoſe hearts ſhall not pity, nor their hands ſpare, untill the purpoſe of the Allmighty be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed upon her, and their Bow ſhall abide in ſtrength in battel, and none ſhall be able to deliver her out of their hands. And People, look not for peace, look not for peace ſo long as her witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crafts remains amongſt you, though you may deſire it, yet ſurely it will be in vain, for the conſummate decree is gone forth againſt all her abominations; therefore as you love your immortal ſouls, and deſire the ſalvation thereof, joyn not with her, but joyn unto the Lord, ſo will you be bleſſed and happy for evermore; ſurely were you ſenſible of the abominations of <hi>Romes</hi> City, you would fear and be aſhamed to call it a <hi>Holy City,</hi> where all manner of impiety is nouriſhed, <hi>viz:</hi> pride, whoredome, murder, and the moſt openly of any place in the world: This teſtimony is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and true concerning it; under pretence of keeping of Hoſpitals for the poor, there is tolleration for Play-houſes, where all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of wickedneſſe is committed, and thoſe muſt pay great ſums
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:171156:28"/>of money to the Pope under pretence of hoſpitality. Oh unheard of wickedneſs! where did ever any of the Saints, or holy men of God countenance any ſuch things? is not this an open ſign they are not of God? did not the Apoſtle ſay, <hi>Above all things keep your ſelves from fornication?</hi> and is not fornication tollerated by a Law? did he not alſo ſay, <hi>Let no corrupt communication proceed out of your mouths?</hi> and are not Comedies and Stage-Playes nothing elſe but ſuch like wickedneſs? and yea, thither do reſort the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of the Clergy-men, <hi>Cardinals,</hi> and the like; and do ye think God beholds not theſe things? yea verily, and his fury is kindled hot againſt it: And in their open Market-places there is Conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, Pupit-Playes, and the like, to amaze and draw the minds of people after vanity; is this the fruits of an holy City? nay, its the fruits of Hell. Do not <hi>Cardinals</hi> (out of which they make <hi>Popes,</hi> from whom come your chiefeſt Pardons for ſins) go up and down in ſuch pride and pomp, as is not uſual amongſt the Princes of this world, with great trains of men after them and before them bare-headed, and their Gowns held up before them; was this the practice of the Saints? Search and ſee, and be no longer deceived with lying vanities, by forſaking your own mercies. In the Scripture is recorded of <hi>Elders</hi> to overſee the Churches, which ſignifieth properly Biſhops, which whoſoever deſireth, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires a good Office, even to be an Elder in the Church, and Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Gods people, but ſuch were to be grave ſober men, <hi>not given to filthy lucre, nor wine, the husband of one wife, and of good report, that he might be a good example to others.</hi> But the title and name of a <hi>Cardinal,</hi> who brought them in, let the wiſe in heart judge; for <hi>Cardinal</hi> ſignifieth properly <hi>Supream,</hi> as your own Catechiſme teacheth, which is againſt Chriſts Doctrine, who ſaid, <hi>He that would be greateſt amongſt them, let him be ſervant unto all.</hi> So Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple come to the Light of Chriſt in you, and with it <hi>Try all things, and hold faſt that which is good; And if any preach any other Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine than this which hath been preached, let him be accurſed,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>yea though themſelves or an Angel from Heaven.</hi> So whoſoever keepeth up Superiority in the Church of God, preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth another Doctrine, for they were all Brethren.</p>
            <p>And again, In <hi>Rome</hi> there is men they call <hi>Biſhops,</hi> but they dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from them whom the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, let him which readeth
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:171156:28"/>judge, who ride up and down in round Caps, and green Ribbons, ſuch as fools uſe to wear, and in great pomp, far from examples of ſobriety, and patterns of holineſſe to others, but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, examples of folly and vanity; and inſtead of being huſbands to one wife, marriage is forbidden amongſt them, which is a <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Devils,</hi> which the Spirit did ſpeak expreſſely ſhould come; and how theſe men govern their families, may be clearly ſeen by tollerating of whoredome in ſuch an open manner, <hi>But whoremongers God will judge,</hi> and all who tollerate and uphold them ſhall in no wiſe be cleer thereof, for they are not ignorant that the Scripture ſaith, <hi>That the wrath of God is revealed from Heaven againſt all ungodlineſſe, and unrighteouſneſſe of men;</hi> and notwithſtanding, are not onely wicked and ungodly themſelves, but tollerate and take pleaſure in them which commit all iniquity with greedineſs: And this is the apparent fruits of that ye call <hi>The Holy City, where the Whore ſitteth at the Chappel dore,</hi> to be hired of men: Oh curſed abomination! that ſuch a place ſhould be called <hi>A Holy City;</hi> but this painting wherewith this impudent Harlot is painted ſhall decay, and all Nations ſhall ſee her ſhame, and the true Holy City ſhall be made manifeſt unto the ſons of men, let down from Heaven as a Bride adorned for her Husband, into which nothing that worketh an abomination or a lye can enter, though the Gates thereof are never ſhut, but ſtand open day and night, in which they ſhall not need the light of the Sun, nor the Moon to give them light who walk therein, <hi>but the Lamb ſhall be the light thereof, and they ſhall reign for ever and ever.</hi> But in <hi>Rome</hi> they muſt have wax Candles to give them light at noon-day, and all manner of abominable works are committed therein, even as <hi>Sodom</hi> and the Inhabitants of <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> whoſe meaſure of iniquity never exceeded them. This is not written from a ſpirit of envy or malice, but from a ſimple heart, being truly moved of the Lord thereunto, that the ſimple may come to underſtand and conſider what they are a doing, and repent and turn to the Lord to worſhip him in Spirit and in Truth, for ſuch onely he hath regard unto, and they who refuſe ſuch a viſitation of love, he will ſurely ſmite with a Curſe, which they will in no wiſe eſcape: Therefore whileſt you have time prize it, before it be too late, for the Lord waiteth to be gracious unto you.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:171156:29"/>
            <p> Oh thou Nation of <hi>France!</hi> though thine iniquities hath ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed many, yet the Lord ſtands at the door of your hearts and knocks, and if any open to him in this the day of his love, he will come in and ſup with him, and make his abode there, ſo will you become a holy habitation, and Temple for the Lord to dwell and abide in, ſo ye will not need to go to <hi>Rome</hi> to fetch pieces of dead mens bones, nor Pardons, as murderers and all manner of unclean perſons do, which ſhe receiveth and harboureth as good Chriſtians, and will give them Pardons as many as they will; and thus is the hands of the wicked ſtrengthned under the name of <hi>Peters Succeſſor,</hi> who was a true witneſſe againſt all ſin and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe whatſoever, who did not ſettle himſelf in an earthly poſſeſſion, for he was not his own, but the Lords, who ſaid unto him, <hi>When thou waſt young thou girdedſt thy ſelf and went whither thou wouldeſt, but now thou art old, another ſhall gird thee, and thou ſhalt go whither thou wouldeſt not;</hi> which is far from the Popes example, juſt as light is from darkneſſe.</p>
            <p>Oh ye Inhabitants of the Earth! my bowels, my bowels yearneth towards you and your captivated ſtate, my ſoul pityeth to ſee how the ſhadow of death hath overſhadowed you, by which means you are kept in ſore captivity and bondage; but the Lord God of my life hath compaſſion on you, and if you do not wilfully count your ſelves unworthy of his tender compaſſion, by refuſing his love, he will rend the Vail from off your hearts, and will cauſe the Light of the glorious Goſpel to ſhine therein, which will give you the light and knowledge of himſelf, in the face of Jeſus Chriſt, that ye may know that glory, honour, and praiſe belongeth only unto him, &amp; not unto man, from whom ye are to ceaſe, for his breath is in his noſtrils, and is nothing to be accounted of; and make not fleſh your arm, leaſt inſtead of a bleſſing, the everlaſting curſe, ſhame, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion come upon your heads for ever: Therefore give up your ſelves unto the Lord in obeying his Light in all things, that you may come to witneſſe a ſanctified ſtate even in Soul, Body and Spirit, that holy, pure, and undefiled Temples your bodies may be for the Lord to take delight to dwell and walk therein, which is the end of all Miniſtrations Types and Shaddows, for this ends them all, even to witneſſe the <hi>Immanuel,</hi> which is by Interpretation <hi>God with us,</hi> or <hi>in us;</hi> and this is the miſtery which hath been
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:171156:29"/>hid from Ages and Generations, even Chriſt in his people, the hope of their glory. So read, and the Lord give you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to know the things which belongs to your peace and everlaſting reſt, which if you turn to the Light of Chriſt Jeſus in you, they ſhall not be hid from your eyes; for as it is written, <hi>The light of the righteous ſhineth more and more untill it comes to a perfect day.</hi> So if you turn to the righteous Light which condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth you for ſin, then a perfect and true diſcovery of all things will be made manifeſt unto you, but if you hate the Light, and bring not your deeds unto it, ye will be as the wicked that walk in darkneſſe, and know not at what they ſtumble; ſo be wiſe leſt this ſaying come juſtly upon your heads, as it is written, <hi>The won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers ſhall periſh, for God is working a work-in theſe dayes, which ye cannot believe, though it be told you.</hi> A warning from the Lord God of Heaven and Earth is this day unto you all, whoſe day is ſprung from on high, and hath viſited the ſons of men, for he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth not in the deſtruction of any of you, but rather deſireth that you ſhould turn from your ſins and live, for our God is a God of mercy and judgement; therefore if you turn unto him by true repentance, and forſake your ſins, which is the only true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, never to be repented of, in which you will come to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe judgement and mercy to meet together, and righteouſneſſe and peace will embrace each other in you, which is the onely happy and bleſſed ſtate, which never can be known or witneſſed but by the death of the man of ſin, for that nature can never come to have peace, but horror and judgement for evermore. Theſe are words of love and truth unto you all, in and through a true lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of all your immortal ſouls, who is ready to ſacrifice his life for his vileſt enemies, even for thoſe who revile, perſecute, and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon him, as he is at this day for the teſtimony of a good Conſcience, who cannot bow to an Idol, nor an Idol-maker, but beareth witneſſe againſt them all, as the Lambs followers ever did in all Ages and Generations, from righteous <hi>Abel</hi> unto this day, who was a true Sufferer in innocency, and therein finiſhed his courſe, as a true and faithful example for all as ſhould follow after, it being the ſeed of the Bond-woman, which perſecuted the ſeed of the Free-woman, which kept the Commandements of God, though it never perſecuted any, but loveth all, even the whole Creation
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:171156:30"/>of God without reſpect of perſons, for this cauſe hath it ſuffered by the hands of unreaſonable men, even in ſeeking for to reclaim them from the evil of their wayes, that they might not periſh therein, (for it is the love and deſire of God towards the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the Earth) and in this work many have been impriſoned, ſtocked, ſtoned and put to death, all which they have born like Lambs, as the Lamb was their Example, <hi>Who was as a Lamb led to the ſlaughter, and as a Sheep before the Shearers is dumb, ſo he open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not his mouth.</hi> This is the true Chriſtian, and Lambs life, <hi>Who is able to declare his Generation?</hi> And ſuch is every one that is born of the Spirit, even as <hi>the wind that bloweth where it liſteth, and men hear the ſound thereof, but knoweth not whence it cometh, nor whither it goeth.</hi> And this is the cauſe why all thoſe that are born of the Spirit, are hated and deſpiſed of men, and a wonder un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, even becauſe they know not the birth which is of God, which is undefiled and incorruptible, becauſe this life is hid with Chriſt in God, being tranſlated as <hi>Enoch</hi> was, whoſe life the ſons of men could not ſee becauſe they looked upon him with that eye which counted Chriſt Jeſus but a natural man, even the ſon of a Carpenter, and the like; and indeed it is the furtheſt the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral eye can ſee, though never ſo much endued with earthly wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and knowledge; for amongſt the wiſeſt in that time, and in all Ages, whether Scribes, Doctors, and Learned men, Chriſt was judged to be the ſon of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and of earthly kindred and parentage; therefore beware how you judge of theſe things ye ſons of men, for though the ſpiritual man judgeth all things, yet he himſelf can be judged of no man. This is the naked truth of God unto you all, that ye may be warned to take heed what you do, and what ſpirit you joyn unto, and with what, and in what ye judge, leaſt you judge with that ſpirit that is to be judged, and ſo fall the deeper into condemnation, and ſo heap coals of fire upon your own heads againſt the day of wrath. Remember it is <hi>Judge not leaſt ye be judged, for all judgement is committed unto the Son,</hi> and only in him, in whom he liveth, and is made manifeſt, can any judgement be aright concerning the things of God; and to the true knowledge of this righteous judgement, did the true Chriſtians come unto; for the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid unto them, <hi>Know ye not that we ſhall judge Angels? which could never be,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:171156:30"/>without the judgement of the Son of Righteouſneſſe, who lived and reigned in them.</hi> And this did he ſpeak unto them, when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved them for going to Law one with another, and that before the unjuſt; <hi>Why</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>do ye not rather ſuffer wrong?</hi> which words ſtandeth a witneſſe againſt the Pope, and all his Adherents, which in <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf theſe things almoſt dayly may be ſeen, even amongſt themſelves, ſuing one another for Curates places, and ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for titles of honour; theſe things are well known to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of <hi>Rome,</hi> for it is evidently known, and manifeſt among them, and the heads being thus corrupted, the whole body cannot but be all infected with the ſame diſeaſe, ſuing and haling one another before Judgement-Seats, which the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily a fault amongſt them which ſo did;</hi> and by this unchriſtian-like means, is there ſwearing and forſwearing amongſt them, which is out of the Doctrine of Chriſt Jeſus, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all, but let your yea be yea, and your nay be nay in all your communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for whatſoever is more than theſe cometh of evill:</hi> So ye may ſee how ye have been taught and led in blindneſs, and all under the name of Chriſtianity, but wholly out of the life thereof, for ſaith Chriſt, <hi>If any man take thy cloak, forbid him not to take thy coat alſo; and if any ſmite thee on the one cheek, turn to him the other alſo:</hi> But how theſe things are obſerved amongſt you, let the Light of Chriſt Jeſus judge; a true Chriſtians life is to bear all things, and not <hi>to overcome evill with evill,</hi> but on the contrary, <hi>overcome evill with good;</hi> and he which doth thus, that man ſhall be bleſſed in his deed, and may in truth call Chriſt <hi>Lord,</hi> for he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth the things which he ſaith; but they who follow the <hi>Romiſh</hi> practices, ſhall be numbred among the Unbelievers, for the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle exhorteth not only to be <hi>Hearers of the Word, but Doers alſo, For it ſhall be more tollerable in the day of Judgement for Sodome and Gomorrah, than for thoſe who know the will of God, and do it not;</hi> for if one ſpeak unto you in the ſpirit of meekneſſe and love, exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you to repentance, and telling you the end of the wicked; we know that ſay you, thou telleſt us nothing but what we know already; I ſay the greater is your condemnation, yea, it will go better with the <hi>Indians</hi> in <hi>America,</hi> than with you in the day of tryal, than for many of you, for whom my ſoul hath, and doth mourn, who are ſetting up lyes, crying <hi>The Catholick, the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:171156:31"/>Church</hi> and <hi>Roman.</hi> You are its true of the <hi>Romiſh Religion,</hi> but the <hi>Apoſtolick</hi> you are far from, for ye are not like them any way in any one thing, yet in the name ye boaſt, and count none Chriſtians but thoſe who are conformable to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which is hard to be uttered, it is ſo abominable and wicked, as hath been ſhewed in many things, yea they are grown ſo hard in their abominable Imaginations, that it is common for them to make the picture of a woman with a child in her lap playing with a Dog, and ſay it is the picture of Chriſt, yea with a child on the ground, and its armes about the dogs neck, and ſay the ſame of it.</p>
            <p>Oh unheard of darkneſſe and wickedneſſe is this! and theſe things may be commonly ſeen as one paſſeth along the ſtreets, and is not a ſecret thing; this is the fruits of your ancient Religion, and truly it is ſo ancient as the man of ſin, as appeareth by the fruits thereof; for if one ſpeak but againſt an Image, though it be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely forbidden of the Lord, yet you are ready to tear him in pieces for it, which neither is, nor never was the Life or Spirit of a Chriſtian; but through ſuch doings as theſe, the very name of a Chriſtian is an Abomination amongſt many, even to <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>Jew,</hi> even in cheating and cozening, ſwearing and lying, and open Abominations, which cauſeth them to blaſpheme the name of Chriſt; therefore will the unreſiſtable vengeance of God come irreſiſtably upon you ſuddenly, <hi>except you repent,</hi> and plead no longer antiquity for your Religion, ſeeing it is but of ſin and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, in which you openly live, as all the heathen and profane ever did, yea groſſer Idolatry is not to be found amongſt the ſons of men, than is in the Territories and Dominions of <hi>Rome</hi> this day; though ye ſeek to paint your ſelves over with the name of God, ye do but ſhew the more to every one that is not wilfully blind that ye are of Miſtery <hi>Babylon,</hi> the Mother of Harlots, (Mark that) whoſe children are ſuch as hold the truth in unrighteouſneſs, and have changed the glory of the incorruptible God as much as in you lyeth, though his glory cannot be changed into fleſh, but you have perverted his true worſhip into a lye, and make Images, and proſtrate your ſelves before them, and yet ſay it is not Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry; this is miſtery <hi>Babylon,</hi> which is now made manifeſt, Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Honour and Praiſe be to the Lord God for ever, and let all the faithful ſay <hi>Amen;</hi> for the ſecrets of the Whore is laid open
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:171156:31"/>with her Abominations, and the place of her torment is prepared for her, who hath thus made the Nations drunk with the Cup of her fornication, out of which the Kings of the earth have been made drunk; and not only have compelled the people of their Nations, but others, which thing will be heavy in the end, if they repent not before it be too late, for God is a righteous Judge, who will render to every one according to their works, without reſpect of perſons, time or places.</p>
            <p>Therefore be wiſe O ye Kings, be inſtructed O ye Judges of the Earth, and ſerve the Lord with fear, and rejoyce with tremb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in your Generation, and beware of perſecuting of any peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for that will unthrone you, if ye meddle with the Throne of God, which is the Conſciences of men and women: Therefore let it ſuffice you, that your ſword be turned againſt the evil-doer in the Land, ſo will you be a praiſe to them that do well, and bleſſed will you be of the Lord if ye put this in effect, to wit, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe and expel Idolatry, lying, ſwearing, drunkenneſſe, and whoredome in the Land where ye are Rulers, but if ye ſuffer thoſe things to abound as they do this day in this Nation, then know aſſuredly, as the Lord God lives, who hath created the Heavens and the Earth, ye ſhall be expelled, and thoſe who ſhall be found more worthy than you, ſhall be exalted in your ſtead, though the Lord may take them from the Sheepfold, as he did <hi>David;</hi> and think not to ſtand becauſe of your greatneſs and ſtrength, or by the multitude of an hoſt: Remember <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> whom the Lord humbled unto the duſt, and made him to know that the Moſt High ruleth and reigneth in the Kingdomes of men.</p>
            <p>Therefore ye Rulers of this Nation, to you do I ſpeak in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, I ſay hear and give ear, and the words of my mouth ſhall be the words of truth and life unto you, if ye receive them; but if ye ſlight and reject them, and will have none of the counſel of the Allmighty, which through me is proffer'd freely unto you, that ye may be warned from the evil which is to come, then know aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that blackneſſe and darkneſſe ſhall be your portion and habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for ever, and Gods dreadful face you ſhall never ſee but in judgement: therefore I ſay give over, for the Lord is raiſing to himſelf a Seed and People in this Nation, which ſhall ſerve him with fear and trembling, and hath purpoſed to eſtabliſh them in
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:171156:32"/>peace and righteouſneſſe in this Land, that living examples they may be unto all the Inhabitants about them; and this hath the Lord determined to do in thee O <hi>France:</hi> Therefore as I ſaid, ye Judges, Rulers, Officers, Counſellors, and King, be ye warned as from the Lord, that ye touch them not though you may have many falſe accuſations againſt them and reports, as people not fitting to live upon the earth, as the innocent was in all Ages, ſo reported to be, as people being deſtructive to Law, Rulers, and Government, and the like, and enemies to the King, Oh let this word be turned againſt theſe falſe Accuſers, and beware of touching the Innocent, for for their ſakes the Lord will rebuke Kings, and he is the ſame as ever he was: And this is a true and faithful warning and prophecy which ſhall ſhortly come to paſſe, that when it come you may not be ignorant thereof, and be left without excuſe. Remember <hi>Nineveh,</hi> who at the preaching of <hi>Jonas</hi> repented; and do ye take warning in time; Conſider and lay it to heart, and look through the Nations ye Rulers thereof, and weigh the thing ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in your ſecret parts, whether <hi>Nineveh</hi> or any other Nation could abound more in abomination than this Nation, or that the city of <hi>Sodome,</hi> or the inhabitants of <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> was more in luſt, pride, and fulneſſe of bread then <hi>Paris</hi> ſurely is; nay, the like was hardly to be found, or paraleld in all generations for pride, hypocriſie, luſt, deceit, and murder, and whatſoever is evill: Therefore I ſay againe, Be ye warned, and take diligent heed that ye perſecute not any whom the Lord is raiſing up amongſt you, bringing and ſending amongſt you, to bear witneſſe unto, or againſt any thing, even againſt the grievous Idolatry and whoredome which aboundeth amongſt you, and in all the Land; and if ye inſtead of receiving their teſtimonies, perſecute and impriſon them, or doe them any harm, <hi>better it were that a mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone were put about your necks, and that ye were caſt into the midſt of the Sea,</hi> for the Lord will avenge their innocent cauſes, and utterly overturn their oppreſſors, and will rebuke Kings for their ſakes, yea, Potentates, Armies, Judges, and Rulers, as he hath done already in the Land of <hi>England;</hi> and he who is mightier then the mightieſt is on their parts, and will rebuke and tear in pieces their adverſaries, for the Lord hath long born the iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of this Nation, and his righteous Spirit hath long been grieved,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:171156:32"/>and he hath looked down out of his holy habitation amongſt you, and beholdeth your ſtate, and ſeeth that none of you ſo much as conſider the cauſe of the needy and oppreſſed, ſo as to eaſe their burthens, but every one of you ſtriving to maintain his own luſt by cruelty, fraud, and oppreſſion, the like is not to be found in any Nation; but the Lord will break the bonds of oppreſſion, and the oppreſſed ſhall goe free, and be ſet at liberty to Gods endleſſe praiſe for ever.</p>
            <p>The mighty and terrible day of the Lord God is come and is at hand, wherein the hearts of all ſhall be made manifeſt, and accordingly ſhall every one be judged; therefore I ſay again and again, be ye warned how ye touch or meddle with any who ſhall turn to the Lord in this the day of his eternall power, for they will be ſuch as will in the power and love be made to deny all deceit and flattery, which aboundeth amongſt you, and if for ſo doing you cauſe them to ſuffer, wrath ſhall be your portion and augmented amongſt you, even upon your own heads, for the Lord hath purpoſed that his own ſeed ſhall be ſet at liberty to live and reign over all deceit and deceivable works for ever, and this will he doe to the utter confuſion of all who ſhall op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him.</p>
            <p>And thou ſeed of the moſt high God in this nation, lift up thy head <hi>for thy Redeemer draweth neere to deliver thee,</hi> though thou lyeſt low in the deeps, yet will his owne arm make way for thee to come forth, (as it did in the days of old,) he will rend the vail of <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> darkneſſe, and diſmount the charriots of thy fierce perſecutors, ſo as they ſhall never be able to overtake thee, yea, he will di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the waters of the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Sea, and cauſe thee to goe through as on dry land, in which thy enemies ſhall be overwhelmed for ever and ever; yea the waves of his wrath ſhall cover their heads, and they ſhall be drowned in the bottomleſſe deeps of utter confuſion in thy ſight, and a ſong of praiſes ſhall be put into thy mouth, even as the ſong of <hi>Moſes,</hi> thou tender lamb, and thou ſhalt bear away the ſpoil of thine enemies; and though after all this thine incounters may be many ere thou obtain the promiſed land, yet fear not thou worm, the Lord God Almighty taketh thy part, who will be with thee in the fire, and in the water; my ſoul hath partaken with thee of thy pangs, and thy bruiſes,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:171156:33"/>and fore oppreſſions, and to this day doe I ſuffer with thee, and have true experience of <hi>thy Redeemer that liveth</hi> and ſurely will deliver thee; though thou lyeſt in the deepeſt deeps, and no eye pitieth thee or hath compaſſion on thee, though thou art as a ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worm troden under foot of every one, though thy enemies make long furrows over thy back, yet be thou comforted, thy God hath vowed thy deliverance, and it haſtneth apace, <hi>thy poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion is prepared in a goodly heritage, for in a pleaſant Land ſhall thy lot be:</hi> Though <hi>Eſau</hi> may ſeek thy precious life, and <hi>Iſhmael</hi> mock thee, and the ſons of <hi>Anack</hi> ſet themſelves againſt thee, yea and <hi>Balaam</hi> ſeek inchantments againſt thee, and <hi>Moab</hi> tempt and ſtrive to lay a ſtumbling block before thee, and the ſons of the mighty, even the ſons of <hi>Anack</hi> poſſeſſe thy land, and ſeek to keep thee out by their mighty ſtrength, yea though all Nations ſhould joyn in one to prevent the decree of the Father, yet ſhall it be all in vain, for <hi>thy Redeemer liveth,</hi> even the mighty God, who is <hi>the Holy One of Iſrael,</hi> who will grind them to powder: Oh thou afflicted worm! thine enemies are many, and that my ſoul knoweth right well; therefore am I made willing to take a part with thee, knowing that alſo thy deliverer is mightier then the mightieſt of them, before whom all Nations are but as the drop of a bucket, or as ſtubble; therefore none ſhall be able to prevent his purpoſe concerning thy deliverance thou innocent one, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved of thy God, to whom <hi>all his promiſes are Yea and Amen,</hi> who hath promiſed and vowed thy deliverance, though it be to the deſtruction of all fleſh, and wo, wo will be unto them who ſhall ariſe up againſt thee to hinder thy paſſage into the land of reſt: The Lord hath bowed down his ear from his holy habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto the cry of thine oppreſſions, and his bowels are moved with compaſſion for thee, and as thou haſt been a long ſufferer in the earth, ſo ſhalt thou have dominion over all even in thy God, for he will rend the vail of <hi>Egyptian</hi> darkneſſe, ſo ſhall many come to ſee and deſire thy beauty, and deſire after thy preſence, even as a ſpouſe deſireth the preſence of her bridegroome after her firſt eſpouſall; yea, unto thee oh Seed ſhall the gathering of the Nations be, and the Kings of the Earth ſhall bring their glory and honour unto thee, and Crowned ſhalt thou be with the Dominion of thy God for evermore; the mouth of the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:171156:33"/>Lord hath ſpoken it, and will haſten the day of thy Redemption; though through envy thou haſt been ſold into <hi>Egypt,</hi> and eſteemed as a Bond-ſlave, and put under in the dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, becauſe thou canſt not conſent unto the abominations, and unto the love of men, yet thy God ſhall raiſe thee over all, to reign in dreadful dominion for ever, and thine enemies ſhall be made to come bending unto thee, yea even the ſons of thoſe who had thee in deriſion, ſhall be laid low at thy feet: Thou greatly Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved and begotten of my Father, thy beauty hath overcome my heart, <hi>I am one with thee in the deepeſt of afflictions,</hi> and ſo am made willing to ſuffer with thee, until thou art by the outſtretched Arm and mighty Power of thy God, raiſed up to poſſeſs the Gates of thine enemies; the only bough thou art, whoſe branches ſhall run over, yea, a double portion hath my God for thee in ſtore; though at preſent thy viſage is more marred than the face of any man, ſo that the ſons of men can ſee no beauty in thee, that they ſhould deſire thee, yet when the meaſure of thy ſufferings is up, the ſplendor of thy beauty ſhall pierce through and amaze the hearts of many, for it ſhall ſhine as the Stars of the Firmament, ſo that only thy life ſhall be deſired in the whole earth, and thou ſhalt be the only deſired of all Nations; becauſe thou haſt been the only rejected, therefore thou ſhalt over all reign for evermore. Oh thou Holy One, though thou haſt not had whereon to lay thine head amongſt the Kingdomes of men, yet it is thy right only to reign; therefore ſhall overturnings, overturnings be, until thou art raiſed and haſt taken the Dominions of the whole earth, for to that end waſt thou brought forth out of the boſome of thy father; thou art the Stone which the builders have rejected, but thou ſhalt become the head of the Corner, and all who do riſe up againſt thee, ſhall fall, becauſe <hi>no weapons formed againſt thee ſhall proſper,</hi> and every tongue which riſeth up againſt thee, thou ſhalt condemn; this is thy heritage becauſe of the righteouſneſs of thy God; a Sword and Bow is prepared for thee to go forth to battel, and thou ſhalt ſheath it in the fleſh of Kings and mighty men of the earth, for thou art the Battle-Ax of the Lord, and with thee will he beat Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to powder; therefore bleſſed ſhall he be that ſhall joyn unto thee in this the day of thy controverſie with the Sons of men, for if they receive thee not, but ſtand againſt thee, then ſhalt thou
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:171156:34"/>grind them to powder: And becauſe of this, wo, wo unto the hypocrite, wo unto the ſwearer, who unto the liar, wo unto the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterer, yea, wo unto the inhabitants of the earth, who ſhall joyn with the Dragon in war againſt thee, thou ſhalt command the holy Angels of the Father, which ſhall attend on thee continually, to bind and to caſt into the pit of utter darkneſs for evermore, out of which there ſhall be no redemption.</p>
            <p>Therefore be ye warned O ye Kings, Judges, and Rulers of this Nation and people, not to meddle in this matter, for as ſure as the Lord God liveth, who hath created the Heavens and the Earth, theſe things ſhall ſurely come to paſs; and it will be a folly for you to take counſel of the Sorcerers, Enchanters, and Deviners, for no ſuch thing ſhall be able to prevail againſt the holy anointed one of the Lord, but as I have ſaid, through the holy Spirit of the Lord (if ye fall not upon him) ye will ſurely be ground to powder; and though his coming may be contrary to the expectation of all fleſh, marvel not at it, for it was ever ſo, that the Princes of the world never knew him, though never ſo wiſe, for if they had, they would never have crucified him: And remember what was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the Prophet concerning the way of God, who had it from the mouth of the Lord, ſaying, <hi>My wayes are not your wayes, nor my thoughts your thoughts; but as the Heavens are higher than the Earth, ſo are my wayes higher than yours, and my thoughts higher than your thoughts,</hi> ſaith the Lord of Hoſts: Therefore marvel not at the coming and eſtabliſhing of his only begotten Son in this Nation, as he hath purpoſed in all Nations, I ſay, marvel not though it be to the deſtruction and overturning of all outward glory: Therefore if any in whom he is witneſſed to live and reign, be cauſed and compelled to come before you, and they cannot bow unto you witt Hat or Knee, as all manner of flatterers and diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers do, be ye warned even from the Lord God of life, that ye touch not nor hurt them for theſe things, for if ye do, know aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly that God Almighty will avenge their Cauſe evidently amongſt you who ſhall thus do, for God is jealous of his honour, and he will not give it unto another; and ſo beware that ye reſpect not the perſons of any in judgment, leſt the Lord rebuke you for it, and everlaſting ſhame and reproach come upon your heads for ever; for <hi>He which reſpecteth perſons</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:171156:34"/>ſin, and is convinced by the Law for a Tranſgreſſor;</hi> mark that, the righteous Law convinceth him for a tranſgreſſour, which ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not reſpect perſons in judgment;</hi> they being ſuch who held not the faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Lord of Glory (who reſpecteth not perſons) they having their Lord and Maſter for an example, who reſpected not the perſon of any man, and ſaid, <hi>How can ye believe, who ſeek honour one of another, and ſeek not the honour which comes from God only?</hi> So they who ſeek the honour, and they who give it are all one, even unbelievers and tranſgreſſors; for ſo faith the wiſe man alſo, <hi>It is not good to have reſpect to perſons, for for a piece of bread ſuch an one will offend:</hi> And the thing is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent amongſt you from the Prieſts and people <hi>who have mens per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in admiration, becauſe of advantage;</hi> ſearch and ſee whether any of theſe things be not ſo, yea or nay, with the pure Light of Chriſt Jeſus, which ſhineth in all your Conſciences, which repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth for ſin, and will make all the works of darkneſs manifeſt unto you, as you diligently heed it, and follow it, and love it; <hi>while you have the Light, walk in the Light, that you may be children of the Light,</hi> leaſt it be taken from you, and given to them which are faithfull: Therefore I warn and adviſe you in the everlaſting bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of love, not to ſlight, but prize the day of your viſitation, for the day-ſpring from on high hath viſited you, as I have already ſaid; therefore whilſt yet a time and day is in your hand improve it, that the bleſſing of the moſt high God may be upon you and your poſterity for ever, but if you harden your hearts, and reject this counſel and warning of love, which is freely tendered unto you, then do ye hear the word of the Lord God of Heaven and Earth unto you, who will not be mocked; thus ſaith the Lord, If you harden your hearts againſt me, my unreſiſtible vengeance ſhall come upon your life, as the unreſiſtible Waves of the Sea when mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with a tempeſtuous wind, which ſhall even devour and ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low you up at once, &amp; none ſhall be able to deliver you out of my hands, my fury ſhall come forth againſt you like a mighty wind; that none knoweth from whence it ariſeth, which ſhall ſcatter, break and tear you to pieces. This is the Word of the Lord unto you all, who is righteous in mercy and judgment, and <hi>unto them that fear my name,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>and embrace my counſell, even to you ſhall the Sun of righteouſneſs ariſe with healing under his wings, and ye
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:171156:35"/>ſhall go forth, and grow as Calves of the ſtall; but the proud and thoſe who do wickedly ſhall be as ſtubble which is caſt into the Oven fully dryed:</hi> And this is the determined counſel of the Moſt High con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning all the Nations of the Earth, which are reſpecting of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            <p>Therefore be thou warned, O thou Nation of <hi>France,</hi> to whom. I have been ſent and ſet as a Sign, that thou mayeſt find mercy af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thy long provocation and eſtrangement from God, and that thou may'ſt with a ready mind and willing heart ſubmit to the Kingdome of his Son, which he hath determined to eſtabliſh in the midſt of thee, and that thou mayſt ſubmit unto his Government, for to know him by his Name, whoſe Name is <hi>The Mighty God, the Prince of Peace,</hi> upon whoſe ſhoulder the Government is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which all Nations (either by conſtraint or willingly) ſhall ſubmit unto, even the true <hi>Immanuel, God with man,</hi> whoſe Scepter is free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly held forth, that thou Nation of <hi>France,</hi> with all Nations, might come under it, which if thou doſt, thine inhabitants ſhall be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but if thou refuſeſt, inſtead of bleſſing, that which is tendered unto you ſhall be turned into a curſe for ever.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By a true Servant of the liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, who ſuffers im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment in</hi> Bourg de Ault <hi>neer</hi> Deppt, <hi>known by the Name of</hi> Charles Baily.</signed>
               <dateline>Given forth <date>in the Year 1661.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
